<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-15T21:45:02+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Raheem’s Blog</title><subtitle>My Opiniones on things and stuff</subtitle><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><entry><title type="html">Recipe For A Disaster</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/10/15/disaster.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recipe For A Disaster" /><published>2021-10-15T10:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-15T10:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/10/15/disaster</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/10/15/disaster.html">&lt;p&gt;At your final year in college your graduation project will probably be the most annoying and time consuming task you had to do throughout your entire academic life. And I’m here today to make it even worse, as I hate giving advices to people I’m going to tell you exactly how to make graduation project your way to a mental health facility. So let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choosing-your-group&quot;&gt;Choosing Your Group&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This probably the most important step so please do the minimum amount of thinking before doing it and place your choice solely on one factor and that is how close are you with them. I also recommend not paying any attention to any rational selection criteria like how interested or skilled they are in the topic of your graduation project, or things like their work flow and how much they share your ideas and prioritize the graduation project. I also encourage you to choose someone with contradicted sleep and college schedule so that your chances of meeting with them are way less the less you meet the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choosing-your-topic&quot;&gt;Choosing Your Topic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe this should have been before choosing your group to don’t worry you are in safe hands. Your college will provide you with full support and advices in exchange you’re expected to create a scientific breakthrough in your bachelor degree graduation project so please choose the most advanced and complicated topics that’s currently puzzling the word most elite scientists. My point is: choose a fancy name for your graduation project. Its name has to be prestigious otherwise how would other people know you’re better than them? 
And oh I forgot, please don’t do any initial search about your topic and things like the data you’ll need, limitations, and other boring stuff. These things will magically solve themselves as the semester progress so don’t worry I told you’re in safe hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-supervisor-&quot;&gt;Your supervisor ?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who needs one of these? I’ll tell you: loosers. Wait till the research center of your faculty assign a random supervisor to your project or in case you want to choose from the already available projects you can also choose that randomly, but if you insists you can select a supervisor the same way you choose your group members as mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;workflow&quot;&gt;Workflow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As start working on the project always maintain the least amount of communication between you, your group members, supervisor and the research center. Ensure that problems are discovered as close to the deadlines as possible and then waste that remaining time on blaming each other on who’s fault was that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-the-documentation&quot;&gt;For The Documentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use word or any regular text editor don’t ever waste your time trying to learn latex or anything that’s can make documentation easier. You don’t have to document it step by step, do it all at once and for once no iterative work to gradually enhance your work.
Don’t cite your work I don’t even have to say more about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-the-presentation&quot;&gt;For The Presentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most essential thing in the presentation is to show that you haven’t learned anything useful throughout your work on this project. Pro tip: always agree with the examiners don’t hold your ground and try to defend your work and ideas 
Bounce if you can please show some conflicts or at least ask each other questions about the project during the presentation with your group members this will show the great team spirit that you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations not only you managed to ace your graduation project, you’ve also got the right mindset to start working on your dream career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a short post I know, but I’m kind of busy and not in the mood for writing I’m actully thinking about taking another break until the 17th of November but I’ll probablly publish one or two more before that (as I said before I keep adding to my drafts without being able to finish them) after I finish my degree I’ll try to publish 2-3 post per week unless of course I run out of things to write about but until then I’ll &lt;b&gt;TRY&lt;/b&gt; to keep things shorter and simpler.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">At your final year in college your graduation project will probably be the most annoying and time consuming task you had to do throughout your entire academic life. And I’m here today to make it even worse, as I hate giving advices to people I’m going to tell you exactly how to make graduation project your way to a mental health facility. So let’s get started.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Loneliness</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/10/05/loneliness.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Loneliness" /><published>2021-10-05T10:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-05T10:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/10/05/loneliness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/10/05/loneliness.html">&lt;p&gt;Hello Friend, long time no see, I know I know I missed you too. for me it feels like it been a long time since I wrote anything 
I’ve been busy avoiding my responsibilities and as always not doing what I have to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I’m talking about something that seems very personal, but it’s kind of all I’m thinking about lately (and by lately I mean the past few years). It might be surprising to people who “know” me that something like this consumes a big proportion of my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between all feelings, I think that loneliness is the most felt emotion in my life. since I can remember I’ve always felt like an outcast, I had to pretend to fit in and somehow I was good at it (pretending) so good in fact sometimes I even fool myself and the line gets blurry between my true self and the image I have to maintain in order to drive away my feeling of alienation. This actually made things worse because at the cost of having friends I started to lose my identity 
This may sound strange, but many times I can’t truly decide if my judgment of things and people is my own or it’s just shaped by the opinions of those who I desperately wanted thier approval. maybe that’s why I’m a liverpool fan becuase of thier “You’ll Never Walk Alone” motto I’ve always starved for a sense of belonging to something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-am-i-&quot;&gt;Who am I ?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve progressed in life and started to know more people I started to develop some narratives about my self one to each group of “friends” family members and relatives. I have to stay in character every day all the time and change between them as needed, it hurts it’s mentally exhausting, but being alone is sometimes more painful than being hurt or at least that how I justified it to myself, but now I don’t think that it has to be. Loneliness is like color blindness but for feelings I can’t be truly happy angry or even sad everything is just a pale version of it self. I always wonder if everyone or at least a lot of people do this that’s why I’ve always questioned the genuintiy of any feelings toward me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;i&gt;Loneliness is the price we have to pay for being born in this modern age, so full of freedom, independence, and our own egoistical selves.&lt;/i&gt;”
Sōseki, ‘Kokoro’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A misconception about loneliness is that people sometimes tend to think that loneliness is cuased by family, friends or colleagues but I think loneliness is eternal feeling I think even people in happy relationships and those who have  a loving family can still feel very lonely. Sometimes people don’t even acknowledge it, but there’s like an iceberg of loneliness to each of us  we seek to be understood, like deeply understood, Deep within every human being there still lives the anxiety over the possibility of being alone in the world. But it’s hard to communicate what we truly feel. I strongly believe that no matter how good we know someone and no matter how close we get to them we can’t in our final judgment of that person say we know them 100% even if they wanted to tell us, even if they wanted us to know. There’s always so much to people that you can’t know or comprehend. That’s why I started to take things less personally lately I don’t blame people I don’t hold grudges for someone. But unfortunately more likely than not my understanding for people decisions get confused for a lack of care about them. The way I think about it is that I’m doing people a favor by cutting them off saving them the troubles of dealing with someone who doesn’t even  know who he truly is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;i&gt; But even so, every now and then I would feel a violent stab of loneliness. The very water I drink, the very air I breathe, would feel like long, sharp needles. The pages of a book in my hands would take on the threatening metallic gleam of razor blades. I could hear the roots of loneliness creeping through me when the world was hushed at four o’clock in the morning.&lt;/i&gt;” haruki murakami - wind-up bird chronicles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who’s interested in A.I I wonder if in the future we would be able to create an A.I that’s so good it’s indistinguishable from human. Think of it as a highly sophisticated conversional chat bot where you can choose the theme of the conversation you want to have (or it can determine that automatically) and then generate exactly the perfect conversation for you (does this makes you think about the movie “HER” ?) and think this is achievable but the problem is that humans crave this things from other humans.
Also one thing that this kind of A.I application will never be good at is creating a shared experience that what makes us connect with other people more than anything overcoming problems and enjoying happy moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the feeling loneliness is pretty messed up, still i owe a lot of good things that happened to me to it. If didn’t have the time that was available because my introverted nature I wouldn’t have known half of what I know now. It’s also helps you to understand yourself (and therefore  others) better and reflect on your life decisions  as long as you don’t drift away too much to the dark places your mind can go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;i&gt;The yardstick for a human being is: how long and to what degree he can bear to be alone, devoid of understanding with others. 
A man who could bear being alone during a whole life-time, and alone in decisions of eternal significance, is farthest removed from the infant and the society-person who represent the animal definition  of a human being.&lt;/i&gt;” soren kierkegaard&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember: the time you feel lonely is the time you most need to be by yourself. Life’s cruelest irony.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">Hello Friend, long time no see, I know I know I missed you too. for me it feels like it been a long time since I wrote anything I’ve been busy avoiding my responsibilities and as always not doing what I have to do.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Side Skills You Need To Improve</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/16/Side-Skills.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Side Skills You Need To Improve" /><published>2021-09-16T14:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-09-16T14:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/16/Side-Skills</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/16/Side-Skills.html">&lt;p&gt;A lot of time we tend to underrate some factors that can actually have huge effect on your learning experience and your whole productivity in general. Here I’ll go over some basic skills that I think are essential and can have a tremendous impact on your learning and help you in everyday work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;touch-typing&quot;&gt;Touch typing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think everyone who’s doing some kind of work that’s evolves a Keyboard should know how to type fast. There’s a lot of free websites that teach you how to  master touch typing, I’ll give links and descriptions to them below. typing fast is a very satisfying skill to have  and you’ll feel your progress while doing it which is  great if you impatient or the type of person that loses interest in things quickly when you don’t see fast or direct  results, even though I still type at a pathetic rate of (45-50 Word Per Minute according to 10fastfingers ) and it’s even slower when I write code (because of the  parentheses and stuff) still I’ve came a long way from using my index fingers to type almost everything and I’m still improving. I’m hoping that I’ll be able to reach at least 80 wpm by the end of this year&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;speed-reading&quot;&gt;Speed Reading&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think compared to typing reading is less obvious skill to improve no one thinks that they actually need to improve their reading speed, but just like typing it’s not only about speed but rather the techniques that allow for faster and more efficient output from reading. I learned this the hard way when I was doing literature review for my graduation project and I had to skim through a lot of papers, books and articles I literally had to read pages diagonally because I can’t read everything, I knew that this had to Improve and I have to read faster without sacrifice my comprehension.
Also similar to touch typing there’s a lot of  websites that help you learn techniques and practice them to improve your reading skills 
When you combine this two skills you’ll find yourself saving a good amount of time that you didn’t even knew you were wasting. average person reads from 200 to 300 words per minute but you can reach much higher rates(x2 or x3 !!)  with practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;keyboard-shortcuts-and-basic-command-line&quot;&gt;Keyboard shortcuts and basic command line&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computer aren’t meant to have mouses in fact computers didn’t even have GUI for a good part of thier existence so you can practically get everything done 
Without even moving your hands away from the keyboard or at least minimize this movement. It wasn’t until recently that I knew the shortcut to delete one word or go back/front one word which made me feel like a cave man for spending my life using mouse and deleting character by character. There’s a lot of very useful keyboard shortcuts that can make your life easier you just need to be patient getting used to them and resist the temptation to use regular ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also have to know the basic cmd of your OS you don’t have 
to be a hacker or something just basic navigation and file directory creation and changing and similar stuff
Also if you have a favorite IDE or (any program actually) it will probably has a quite useful keyboard shortcuts which can make you feel more comfortable and productive using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;basic-uiux&quot;&gt;Basic UI/UX&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just some concepts and familiar with  some design tools
You don’t have to be graphic designer or anything fancy just the bare minimum, but it does make the difference if you are in a any computer science discipline you’ll probably(almost certainly) work on a project that has Users so you need to work with the design teams or at least consider that user experience  with yor software and it will also be useful to have some basic knowledge that’s enables you to understand some decisions about that project. 
Programmers tend to forget that most of the users that use their  programs  will have so little knowledge about the application and how optimized and efficient the code was,  UI/UX is your only why to communicate your “amazing” implementation to the user. I won’t lie of out of all skills in this list this is probablly the least urgent, but still very needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;git&quot;&gt;Git&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it seems like no one “gits” it but it is actually a version control tool that helps you maintain version of your code and can make collaboration with other programmers much easier I won’t go into the technical details here I’ll just leave links below.I’ve created my github account in late 2015 and I have a lot of repos (not a lot actually exactly 35), but until now I don’t fully understand how git really works and I Google some basic commands from time to time to remember what they do, Still, it’s essential skill to anyone who writes code ( or actually any modifiable files not necessary code) to be able to work with git&lt;br /&gt;
Add pull, push, commit are basically all that you’ll need to “git” started once you are comfortable with it you be able to reach new levels in your code quality and make working with others much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;latex&quot;&gt;Latex&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All I have to say here is just that if you hate Microsoft Word then you have to learn latex. again this is something I really found helpful in my last academic year and  it’s now my go to text processor for almost every assignment or project.
Latex can be intimidating at first but you quickly get used to it, and similar to all the previous skills it’s actually worth the effort and time you spent acquiring it.
The best way to get started in my opinion is overleaf which is a good website that gets you started quickly without worrying about setups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;invest-in-your-tools&quot;&gt;Invest in your tools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a skill of course but it is worth mentioning here. I’d like to encourage you to invest in your tools for the long term, buy a more comfortable chair, a bigger monitor, a mechanical keyboard (now you know what I want for my next birthday) as long as something makes you more comfortable and productive go for it. If you think this stuffs are kind of expensive or unnecessary you might ending costing your self even more money because you didn’t achieve certain level of competence that you could’ve reached with more supportive environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;typing&quot;&gt;Typing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://typing.com&quot;&gt;typing.com&lt;/a&gt; perfect for beginners if you don’t know where to start&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://monkeytype.com&quot;&gt;monkeytype&lt;/a&gt; my personal favorite for practicing has everything you once you mastered the basics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://10fastfingers.com&quot;&gt;10fastfingers&lt;/a&gt; good place to test your speed and progress&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.keyhero.com&quot;&gt;keyhero&lt;/a&gt; more paractice with interesting qoutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;speed-reading-1&quot;&gt;Speed Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://readspeeder.com&quot;&gt;readspeeder.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spreeder.com/&quot;&gt;spreeder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tDttHr2GadM&amp;amp;t=417s&quot;&gt;great video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;keyboard-shortcuts-and-cmd&quot;&gt;Keyboard Shortcuts and cmd&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.popsci.com/windows-keyboard-shortcuts/&quot;&gt;20 essential Windows keyboard shortcuts that will make you forget your mouse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;uiux&quot;&gt;UI/UX&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tRpoI6vkqLs&quot;&gt;UI Design Fundamentals Crash Course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;git-1&quot;&gt;Git&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/an-easy-beginners-guide-to-git-2d5a99682a4c&quot;&gt;short Tutorial&lt;/a&gt; an easy beginners guide to git&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SWYqp7iY_Tc&quot;&gt;crash course&lt;/a&gt; for git and github&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;latex-1&quot;&gt;latex&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.overleaf.com/learn/latex/Free_online_introduction_to_LaTeX_(part_1)&quot;&gt;overleaf&lt;/a&gt; Free online introduction to LaTeX&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fCzF5gDy60g&quot;&gt;beginner course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wondering why this post came out earlier than you expected it’s because I’m planning on taking a break for the rest of September.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">A lot of time we tend to underrate some factors that can actually have huge effect on your learning experience and your whole productivity in general. Here I’ll go over some basic skills that I think are essential and can have a tremendous impact on your learning and help you in everyday work. Touch typing I think everyone who’s doing some kind of work that’s evolves a Keyboard should know how to type fast. There’s a lot of free websites that teach you how to master touch typing, I’ll give links and descriptions to them below. typing fast is a very satisfying skill to have and you’ll feel your progress while doing it which is great if you impatient or the type of person that loses interest in things quickly when you don’t see fast or direct results, even though I still type at a pathetic rate of (45-50 Word Per Minute according to 10fastfingers ) and it’s even slower when I write code (because of the parentheses and stuff) still I’ve came a long way from using my index fingers to type almost everything and I’m still improving. I’m hoping that I’ll be able to reach at least 80 wpm by the end of this year Speed Reading I think compared to typing reading is less obvious skill to improve no one thinks that they actually need to improve their reading speed, but just like typing it’s not only about speed but rather the techniques that allow for faster and more efficient output from reading. I learned this the hard way when I was doing literature review for my graduation project and I had to skim through a lot of papers, books and articles I literally had to read pages diagonally because I can’t read everything, I knew that this had to Improve and I have to read faster without sacrifice my comprehension. Also similar to touch typing there’s a lot of websites that help you learn techniques and practice them to improve your reading skills When you combine this two skills you’ll find yourself saving a good amount of time that you didn’t even knew you were wasting. average person reads from 200 to 300 words per minute but you can reach much higher rates(x2 or x3 !!) with practice.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What’s The Title of This Post</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/14/No-Title.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s The Title of This Post" /><published>2021-09-14T14:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-09-14T14:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/14/No-Title</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/14/No-Title.html">&lt;p&gt;Posts are piling up in my draft folder and I can’t seem to able to finish any of them. It’s been almost two months since I started this blog and I’ve been writing about very different topics and I don’t even know which topics I should be focusing on, but I realized that there’s agreement that my previous post (which was a tidyverse tutorial) is the least favorite one so far and that’s kind of predicted, most of people aren’t really interested in the technical parts or at least they’re more interested in my ideas and opinions which is a good thing (I guess).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we like reading relatable things? 
Ironically feeling like no one gets us or no one understands our feelings is actually one of the most relatable feelings of this  generation. Maybe it’s because of the alienating nature of today’s society and social media that made us more self centered. We need other people thoughts to validate our own, we like to be given the right to hate or love certain things or people, humans are very biased creatures, and social media makes use of this all the time by subjecting us to specific algorithmic information diet that maximize your time wasted on them which leads to more revenue for them in return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know how relatable my posts are this whole blog idea was something I had in my mind for while, but I wasn’t able to get started until one day I was talking to a friend of mine about things I wanted to do but I didn’t, and blogging was one of them and she told me I should just get started and I’ll have all of her support. I felt very motivated that day and I knew that I should make use of this motivation dose, and that’s basically how this blog came to be.
This made me think: if it wasn’t for that day maybe I would’ve never started this blog. How many other things I could’ve done if I only channeled a temporary surge of motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also remember a similar situation one year ago when I signed up for the Huawei AI associate certificate I didn’t want to take the exam at first for some reasons I thought that wasn’t ready yet and I wasn’t a fifth year student ( the exams were offered as partnership between Huawei and the university for fifth year students or fresh graduates mainly) so I didn’t sign up at first, but then that exam got postponed and some students withdraw and the organizers were looking for people to take their seats and I was like why not ?I won’t let it pass twice, plus I have nothing to lose anyway. I passed the exam and now I’m a certificated Huawei A.I associate and eligible for the Huawei A.I Professional certificate. I’m not fan collecting certificate for the sake of it I believe they can be deceiving, certificate doesn’t prove your skills and knowledge. They are just useful for HR to decide if your CV is relevant or not. I don’t know if this certificate will be useful one day, but it meant a lot for me at that time because for once I saw an opportunity and didn’t shy away from it which is something I rarely do, but I always wished I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter how this blogging thing will go on I will always feel grateful to that friend (and everyone reading this now, I deeply appreciate every single one of you!) And proud of myself because this actually one the very a few things that I wanted to do and ended up doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we’re talking about motivation A while ago I came across this quote “You won’t always be motivated so learn to be disciplined” I guess every one of us gets highly motivated from time to time maybe at the first of the new year, at your birthday, next week or when starting a new semester or job maybe you can even make some promises and plans, but all of this fades away too soon and you find yourself waiting for the next especial occasion to get started.
consistency is a key we’ll eventually get good only at what we do regularly whether that’s a useful thing, harmful thing or total waste of  time. Yes you can actually get good at wasting time and procrastination I’ve been there before (still there maybe, but I’m getting worse hopefully) and it’s actually quite hard to get rid of this habits, but  sometimes I manage to get around my laziness it’s like surfing, most of the time I’m just waiting still doing nothing, but every now and then some waves (bursts of motivation) shows up and I have to decide quickly which one to ride before they disappear. This helps a little but it’s also very inefficient, motivation will only get you so far, you have to maintain a streak, whatever you’re planning to be good at you’ll have to do it daily (or at least very frequently and consistently) no matter what happens in your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in the end what is the title of this post? is it about motivation, the importance of supportive friends in your life or is it about my laziness? I don’t know, I can’t come up with a title, maybe you can help me ?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">Posts are piling up in my draft folder and I can’t seem to able to finish any of them. It’s been almost two months since I started this blog and I’ve been writing about very different topics and I don’t even know which topics I should be focusing on, but I realized that there’s agreement that my previous post (which was a tidyverse tutorial) is the least favorite one so far and that’s kind of predicted, most of people aren’t really interested in the technical parts or at least they’re more interested in my ideas and opinions which is a good thing (I guess).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TidyTutorial</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/06/Tidytutorial.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TidyTutorial" /><published>2021-09-06T14:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-09-06T14:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/06/Tidytutorial</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/06/Tidytutorial.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;simplest-tutorial-ever&quot;&gt;Simplest Tutorial Ever!!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I promised you to talk more about tidyverse and other R packages, this Tutorial is
only a begging so don’t judge harshly I’m new at this. Initially I did not want to make tutorials on this blog because I believed that the internet is full of them, but one more won’t do no harm right ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;let’s get started, first we need to load the tidyverse library so we can
have access to all the great functions, if you don’t have the tidyverse
library yet you should install it first by running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# install.packages(tidyverse)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;then now we need to load (attach) the package so we can use it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;library&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tidyverse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;like I said before one of the great things in R is that it has many
built in datasets we can choose one to play around with, I’ll use mtcars because it’s one of the most popular datasets with very clear variables&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;when you run this line you will get informations about The mtcars dataset
 (like where it came from, what each variable means, etc…). Now we will
turn it into tibble which is according to tidyverse website : “A tibble, or tbl_df, is a modern reimagining of the data.frame, keeping what time has proven to be effective, and throwing out what is not. Tibbles are data.frames that are lazy and surly: they do less (i.e. they don’t change variable names or types, and don’t do partial matching) and complain more (e.g. when a variable does not exist). This forces you to confront problems earlier, typically leading to cleaner, more expressive code.”  this is optinal however
this Tutorial is so simple this stuff it wont matter but it’s just a habit for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;as_tibble&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 32 x 11
##      mpg   cyl  disp    hp  drat    wt  qsec    vs    am  gear  carb
##    &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
##  1  21       6  160    110  3.9   2.62  16.5     0     1     4     4
##  2  21       6  160    110  3.9   2.88  17.0     0     1     4     4
##  3  22.8     4  108     93  3.85  2.32  18.6     1     1     4     1
##  4  21.4     6  258    110  3.08  3.22  19.4     1     0     3     1
##  5  18.7     8  360    175  3.15  3.44  17.0     0     0     3     2
##  6  18.1     6  225    105  2.76  3.46  20.2     1     0     3     1
##  7  14.3     8  360    245  3.21  3.57  15.8     0     0     3     4
##  8  24.4     4  147.    62  3.69  3.19  20       1     0     4     2
##  9  22.8     4  141.    95  3.92  3.15  22.9     1     0     4     2
## 10  19.2     6  168.   123  3.92  3.44  18.3     1     0     4     4
## # ... with 22 more rows
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that the data has 32 observations and 11 columns, now let’s make use of tidyverse&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;disp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;wt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;am&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 32 x 4
##      mpg  disp    wt    am
##    &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
##  1  21    160   2.62     1
##  2  21    160   2.88     1
##  3  22.8  108   2.32     1
##  4  21.4  258   3.22     0
##  5  18.7  360   3.44     0
##  6  18.1  225   3.46     0
##  7  14.3  360   3.57     0
##  8  24.4  147.  3.19     0
##  9  22.8  141.  3.15     0
## 10  19.2  168.  3.44     0
## # ... with 22 more rows
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The select() function works similar to the SQL statement SELECT, as you
can see it’s very easy to choose certin columns but this is not the true
power of tidyverse the “pipe” %&amp;gt;% is very helpful because now we can chain
commands together, we can select some columns and then select individual
cases given a certain condition like for example “show the displacement
and weight and miles per gallon for all the manual (am == 1) cars in the
dataset”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;disp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;wt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;am&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;am&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 13 x 4
##      mpg  disp    wt    am
##    &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
##  1  21   160    2.62     1
##  2  21   160    2.88     1
##  3  22.8 108    2.32     1
##  4  32.4  78.7  2.2      1
##  5  30.4  75.7  1.62     1
##  6  33.9  71.1  1.84     1
##  7  27.3  79    1.94     1
##  8  26   120.   2.14     1
##  9  30.4  95.1  1.51     1
## 10  15.8 351    3.17     1
## 11  19.7 145    2.77     1
## 12  15   301    3.57     1
## 13  21.4 121    2.78     1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we can add even more conditions and more functions let assume for the
sake of example that there’s something called weight displacement ratio
which is obtained by dividing the displacement of a car by its weight in
1000 of pounds and we want to do this for the manual cars that has high
miles per gallon (let’s assume that this means &amp;gt; 25) we can do all of
this just by running :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Weight_displacemet_ratio&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;disp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;wt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;disp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;wt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Weight_displacemet_ratio&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;am&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;25&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;am&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 6 x 5
##     mpg  disp    wt Weight_displacemet_ratio    am
##   &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;                    &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
## 1  32.4  78.7  2.2                    35773.     1
## 2  30.4  75.7  1.62                   46873.     1
## 3  33.9  71.1  1.84                   38747.     1
## 4  27.3  79    1.94                   40827.     1
## 5  26   120.   2.14                   56215.     1
## 6  30.4  95.1  1.51                   62855.     1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important thing to remember is that the original data is still as it
is its not modified so if you check that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 32 x 11
##      mpg   cyl  disp    hp  drat    wt  qsec    vs    am  gear  carb
##    &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
##  1  21       6  160    110  3.9   2.62  16.5     0     1     4     4
##  2  21       6  160    110  3.9   2.88  17.0     0     1     4     4
##  3  22.8     4  108     93  3.85  2.32  18.6     1     1     4     1
##  4  21.4     6  258    110  3.08  3.22  19.4     1     0     3     1
##  5  18.7     8  360    175  3.15  3.44  17.0     0     0     3     2
##  6  18.1     6  225    105  2.76  3.46  20.2     1     0     3     1
##  7  14.3     8  360    245  3.21  3.57  15.8     0     0     3     4
##  8  24.4     4  147.    62  3.69  3.19  20       1     0     4     2
##  9  22.8     4  141.    95  3.92  3.15  22.9     1     0     4     2
## 10  19.2     6  168.   123  3.92  3.44  18.3     1     0     4     4
## # ... with 22 more rows
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this is very helpful because you don’t want to create new instances of
your dataframe to apply functions to it especially in the first stages
of analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay lets do something fun, hmm lets do a very simple
analysis by plotting very simple boxplot to see if there is difference
in mpg in the groups of cars that have a different number of cylinders&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;as.factor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;box_plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ggplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;aes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;geom_boxplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;box_plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\posts\TidyTut\box1.png&quot; alt=&quot;boxplot&quot; /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy enough, but what an ugly graph lets make things more interesting&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;box_plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ggplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;aes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fill&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;geom_boxplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scale_fill_brewer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;palette&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Set3&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; 
 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;theme_classic&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;labs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Fuel Consumtion Categorized By The Number Of Cylinders&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;subtitle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;(1973-74)&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;caption&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Data from the 1974 Motor Trend US magazine.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tag&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Figure 1&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Number of Cylinders&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Fuel economy (mpg)&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;colour&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Cylinders&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;box_plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\posts\TidyTut\box2.png&quot; alt=&quot;boxplot&quot; /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that cars with fewer number of cylinders have more miles per gallon which means they are more efficient than cars with higher number of cylinders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let see if there is a relationship between the weight of a car and
its gas consumtion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-r highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ggplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;aes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;wt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;geom_point&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scale_color_manual&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;#997777&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;#E69F00&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;#56B4E9&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;theme_minimal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;labs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Fuel economy declines as weight increases&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;subtitle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;(1973-74)&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;caption&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Data from the 1974 Motor Trend US magazine.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tag&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Figure 2&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Weight (1000 lbs)&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Fuel economy (mpg)&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;colour&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Gears&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\posts\TidyTut\sp1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Scatterplot&quot; /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt; 
Looks like heavier cars tends to consume more gallons than lighter ones.  we’ve gain a good amount of overall informations with few steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See? that was very easy don’t
worry if you don’t understand some of ggplot commands and options I
won’t explain it here today I think it deserve its own tutorial(s). The
whole point of this tutorial was to whet your appetite to go try this for
yourself, in future Tuts we will go through more complicated stuff with
more realistic data, for now I think this is enough for a first tutorial I’m just experimenting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hasta luego !&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">Simplest Tutorial Ever!!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tidyverse For A Messy Mind</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/01/tidyverse-intro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tidyverse For A Messy Mind" /><published>2021-09-01T14:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-09-01T14:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/01/tidyverse-intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/01/tidyverse-intro.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-journey-with-r&quot;&gt;My Journey With R&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first started to learn about machine learning and data science it didn’t make any sense for me to learn any other language than python 
It’s easy to learn and code in,
Requires minimum installations of other programs so you can get started quickly, has a library for almost every thing I needed,  and I already had some experience in it from my web development days (back when I was using Django framework) so learning something like R seemed redundant and  unnecessary so I never really cared about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I  didn’t think about R again until my fourth year in college when there was a course on applied statistics which used to be taught in stata and other statistical packages, but lucky for us I think we were the first or second batch to be taught R and I recall that there was some conflicts between the students on which language should be used in the course Python or R, and even though - as I recall- the majority voted for python we were still taught R which turned out to be pretty cool actully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I  won’t lie at first R didn’t seem to offer much more or any thing new because we were studying the basics of the language (variables definitions,  for loops , functions, etc…) and  I was studying it for an exam only (it was the easiest A+ ever by the way), but as always I wish I was told how useful it’s going to be and how important was it to dive deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never opened Rstudio for months after that until the next semester when I had some code assignments in R for time series analysis and survival time analysis courses when I looked through the time series textbook  I was amazed by the beautiful plots and even more surprised by how little R code they used to generate this beautiful plots and so I found out about ggplot package which is a R package for plotting based on the “grammar of graphics” (a layered approach to plotting and visualization) which then lead me to discover the tidyverse packages and Shiny web apps and it was so awesome I wanted to re-learn everything I learned before in Python again in R.
One of the best things I found was the #TidyTuesday challenge on Twitter which is a weekly challenge where people form all over the R community try their data visualization and data analysis techniques on one specific dataset for that week .
You can find a very insightful submissions and some people sometimes share their code and steps it’s really very helpful community. Every week I want to participate in #TidyTuesday but I always forget or just get lazy and procrastinate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being exposed to all of this at the same time felt so overwhelming I literally didn’t know were to start, but learning from my previous mistakes I wanted to learn with minimal resources and because R is so amazing there’s a lot of data to play with and experiment on that comes with R and additonal datasets once you install tidyverse package and so I started to mess around, this turned out to be useful when we had to make a project for the design of experiments course, becuase I didn’t like SPSS graphs and ggplot made the project look much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-i-like-about-tidyverse&quot;&gt;What i like about tidyverse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tidyverse according to thier offical website is “The tidyverse is an opinionated collection of R packages designed for data science. All packages share an underlying design philosophy, grammar, and data structures.” and this meant that it’s so intuitive to use the functions names and the overall work flow becomes much easier, but the real game changer is the pipe operator %&amp;gt;% (a fancier and more recent version is |&amp;gt; it’s not fully adoptedyet) this enables you to chain functions together so the output of one function is the input of the other. This meant you can easily implement a pipeline that reads the data , cleans it (remove null values, impute missing value, drop unimportant columns, etc), then does some filtering and grouping and Finally plotting a beautiful graph, and all of this in one line. Tidyverse made me understand why so many programmers now days prefier functional programming paradigm: much cleaner code easier to implement, test and debug. I’m a lazy person I would like to get as many things done with as few steps as possible tidyverse gives me just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing is the whole  community is so helpful (I already said that but it’s worth repeating) you can find very creative solutions to most of your errors and problems and there’s always new updates and new helpful packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-note&quot;&gt;Final Note&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t want this post to be understood as a comparison between R and Python as I said before I hate comparing technologies 
If you love Python and you feel like everything I said is already available for you in Python in a more convenient way that’s completely fine, but I still think it’s useful to approach things from different perspective, personally I was missing out on a lot of cool things in R. It can actually be beneficial to your Python (or any other language) skills, because similar to learning natural languages learning new one can help you understand the other better. I’ve learned a lot of interesting facts about English after studying Spanish for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of this qoute “from a wider perspective, the tidyverse can be seen as sub-dialect of the R language that is evolving to express ideas and tasks inherent in Data Science workflows and software development. This dialect may not be for everyone, but it does seem to be helping many R fluent data scientists frame their conversations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This  post wasn’t actually meant to be for this week, I was working on something different but it wasn’t ready yet and I didn’t want to lose the momentum. So please excuse me if this seems rushed or short I promise to write more about tidyverse and the most important R packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you interested in learning more I’ll leave this link to this great post &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tidyverse.org/blog/2021/08/teach-tidyverse-2021/&quot;&gt;Teaching the tidyverse in 2021&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you next week!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">My Journey With R When I first started to learn about machine learning and data science it didn’t make any sense for me to learn any other language than python It’s easy to learn and code in, Requires minimum installations of other programs so you can get started quickly, has a library for almost every thing I needed, and I already had some experience in it from my web development days (back when I was using Django framework) so learning something like R seemed redundant and unnecessary so I never really cared about it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I will Stop blogging</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/26/the-end.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I will Stop blogging" /><published>2021-08-26T14:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-26T14:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/26/the-end</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/26/the-end.html">&lt;p&gt;If think this is actually my last blog post then I’m sorry to disappoint you, but I’m not going to stop, at least not for the foreseeable future. Why the drama then? well, I actually thought about quitting before, especially after last post for many reasons, but I reconsidered and decided that I’m not going to. Below I’ll give an explanation to why I thought about stopping this blog, why I changed my mind and when I will really stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reasons-to-stop&quot;&gt;Reasons To Stop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I said many times that the main beneficiary from this blog is me, I still however care about the opinions of the people reading my posts (there’s only about 10 currently) and for some reason there was relatively low feed back especially for the last post and I started thinking the wrong way (like I always do) which is that because how uninteresting they are. I thought “no one asked and no one cares about your opinions, they only interacted with first ones out of pity and now got bored from pretending to care”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason is that I’m a very scattered person who is always obsessed with learning or trying new things (which can be a very bad trait) and between all of this stuff I really want to learn or try blogging is not a priority right? Well no, and I will tell you why in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-will-not&quot;&gt;Why I will not&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all there’s some hidden technical part to this blog for example I have to maintain the code and do some git stuff (basically some commits and pulls and pushs). Also learning something new like markdown which is a more convenient way than html to write posts like this one,  plus This blog is actually made by a Ruby language framework called jekyll ( I never ever wrote a single line in Ruby and probably never will, but am still able to work with it isn’t this amazing ?). These things are not actually complicated, but still in the end they are extra things am learning on the go and they will -hopefully- be useful one day.
Also you might have realized that there’s so many spelling and grammar mistakes and serious lack of fluency (sometimes I forget some words in the middle of a sentence) I never thought about how much I need to improve my writing skills before starting this blog (thanks to you autocorrection), in general, active language skills (speaking and writing) are commonly neglected while learning any language. So to summarize I’m actually learning more about things I didn’t know in addition to the main goal of this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly I have almost always been in similar situations like this, where I go from enthusiasm at the beginning then slowly losing interest until I end up in a half done projects which I completely forgot why I even started it. So this time I want to see things through, I want to know what would happen in the end (if there’s an end to this ) I think had my fair share of (what-if)s so far. Finishing things really improve our mental state since it leaves little to overthink about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-least-comfortable-choice&quot;&gt;The least comfortable choice.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to come up with excuses to give up. The way I thought about this is actually me just being both lazy and coward if you think your content is not good enough you improve it, You don’t just giving up the whole thing. 
I really hope that I’ll be able to do as many uncomfortable things in my life as possible. Almost all of the good things (and people ) require certain level of risk and discomfort at first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-will-i-ever-stop&quot;&gt;When will I ever stop?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I made things clear on why I would keep blogging it’s time to tell you when will I stop. Actually there’s is basically one thing I’m  afraid of becoming which is being fraud. I don’t like pretentious things or people.
There’s a song called “smoke and mirror” by gotye I always feel nervous when listen to it, Because I’m afraid of getting used to people praising my mediocre skills and no I’m not hating on myself here or trying to be humble, but I think that’s they don’t know enough about the things I do to make a good judgment. For example if someone who doesn’t even know what a  web server is kept telling you that you’re a good back-end developer it wouldn’t mean anything to you right ? .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog started to look like a dairy so I’m thinking about making more technical posts next. This makes it 4 out of 4 in august I’m feeling proud actually, might treat myself to an Ice cream or something haha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week midterm will decide if there’s a post or not. Wish me luck !&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">If think this is actually my last blog post then I’m sorry to disappoint you, but I’m not going to stop, at least not for the foreseeable future. Why the drama then? well, I actually thought about quitting before, especially after last post for many reasons, but I reconsidered and decided that I’m not going to. Below I’ll give an explanation to why I thought about stopping this blog, why I changed my mind and when I will really stop.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On The Nature Of Advice</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/20/advices.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On The Nature Of Advice" /><published>2021-08-20T02:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-20T02:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/20/advices</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/20/advices.html">&lt;p&gt;As someone who didn’t like giving or asking for advices, starting a blog where I’m sharing my ideas and opinions might seems like a contradiction, but as I said in the very first post of this blog I’m doing this for my own benefit. whenever I’m writing a new post I’m practically talking to myself, but if someone somehow finds it useful then that’s awesome, but its not my goal to tell people what to do I’m just sharing my thoughts from my humble experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-dont-like-advices&quot;&gt;Why I Don’t Like Advices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I need to make things more clear when I say that I do not like advices. Don’t get me wrong I do believe that sometimes some types of advices  works, I just think that most of “successful” people tend to believe that thier journey is completely replicable when in fact no one’s is. There’s so many examples of very successful people didn’t realize that they were doing the right thing until it eventually paid off  and sometimes they don’t even comprehend how circumstances played in their advantage and how luck can actually determine a lot of your decisions in life. Therefore even when these advices come with good intentions they can lead to serious discouragement and disappointment when they don’t work out well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-one-knows&quot;&gt;No One knows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one know the secrets to success not even great successful people. 
The other day I was reading about Bayesian Statistics and found out that in fact Thomas Bayes who actually came up with the conditional probability equation which we now know as Bayes’s theorem one of the most important theorems in statistics (if not the most ) he never published it because he didn’t think it something of any value in fact it was published after his death and we have Thomas’s friend Richard Price to thank for that, he found it his apartment and arranged it for its posthumous publication (actually while writing this I found this so interesting that it deserves its own whole post). I also remember reading something similar about Franz Kafka the genius novelist who ordered his servant to burn all of his useless mediocre work (in his opinion) after his death, but luckily for humanity his servant didn’t listen to him. 
Some people  just love asking for advices even on obvious things Goerge Hotz the  founder of comma ai (a company that makes self driving cars computers) said this when he was asked about giving advices to this type ofpeople “I will write a self help book and charge 67$ for it then I’m going to write on the very first page of this book: ‘all of this advices are meaningless but you gonna be sucker and buy it anyway’” I loved his answer because sometimes people wants to be told advices just because it would make them feel better about themselves they’ll think just by seeking advices they’re already better people which is nice way to think about yourself I guess, but can be very misleading or even harmful on the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the only type of advices you can actually give are either technical or very specific where you almost giving instructions. You can’t give advice for someone who asks “how can I learn X ?” I don’t know, Google it ? “how can I be good at Y” do it a lot maybe. These types of questions are annoying, I mean a lot of things in this life just kind of work out, you should stop wasting your time looking for advices and short cuts you’ll end up waste more time. If someone would ask me how i managed to get good exam score in a certain course I’d probably tell them to ware blue shirt on the day of the exam, because I remember doing better in exams when I ware blue shirts. This actually as relevant as telling them to study hard or telling them not to skip lectures. I think deep down they know exactly what they should do and what they are really after is the sense of reassurance that comes from people giving us advices because at the end what is an advice anyway? I like to define it as: the best guess to how thinks actually work out to best case scenario (or any good enough scenario that made people ask you for advices )” it’s basically like saying things will be fine if you do this which is something you just cann’t guarantee, “guess” is the  keyword here you never know what really happened. I think you can actually tell a lot about people just by how comfortable they’re with saying “I don’t know”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that my view on this topic is bit exreme and biased maybe because of the many advices that were useless or because of all the times I did the oppiste of what I was told and  things turned out very good. Maybe this whole post will be awkward if one I publish a book or give a talk at some event in which I’m baisclly telling people advices, but who knows maybe I look back at this post few years from now and I’ll feel  proud that I changed the way I think about this. 
Finally if I had to give someone one piece of advice it would definitely be “do not listen to me”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I don’t publish another post next week I’ll probably wont for a long time even though I actually have some drafts for a few more posts but I’m expecting a busy schedule next month so maybe no new post till October.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">As someone who didn’t like giving or asking for advices, starting a blog where I’m sharing my ideas and opinions might seems like a contradiction, but as I said in the very first post of this blog I’m doing this for my own benefit. whenever I’m writing a new post I’m practically talking to myself, but if someone somehow finds it useful then that’s awesome, but its not my goal to tell people what to do I’m just sharing my thoughts from my humble experience.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What I’ve learned from my undergrad years</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/12/undergradute.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What I’ve learned from my undergrad years" /><published>2021-08-12T02:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-12T02:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/12/undergradute</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/12/undergradute.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-ive-learned-from-my-undergrad-years&quot;&gt;What I’ve learned from my undergrad years&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“A university is a collection of buildings where in exchange for all your time, money,  and dignity you’ll get rewarded with a clammy hand shake, some paper with special ribbon on it, and a life time of crippling social regrets.”&lt;/em&gt; This is the opening statement of one of my favorite YouTube videos (I’ll leave a link to it below) I think it’s a good start this post.
Now that I’m at my last semester of college, I find myself thinking a lot about my whole academic life. Few days ago friend of mine was singing a songs which lyrics translates to “All of this was for what “ even thought the context is completely different I started to think: “of what use where all of this courses?” “Will I ever need the informations I learned in that year?”, “What are the real life applications for that concept? why did I even bother with it”. 
In this post I’ll try to summarize my thoughts about my years in college, and what was good and what was not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-lets-start-with-the-good-things&quot;&gt;First let’s start with the good things:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be frank not many of them can be said when we’re talking about my college, but I still can’t say there was none.
I think the best thing for me was that the fact that there’s a lot of people to look up to. I’m talking about alumni that are now working in the biggest tech companies in the world (Google,  Facebook,..)in very exciting careers or doing their post grad studies in leading universities, and they managed to do it in “relatively” short time. These kind of people really gives me hope that if I work hard enough and with little luck great things might happen to me too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think another good thing I learned is to accept my mediocrity. Don’t get me wrong I still do believe that we should try to be better every single day, but what I mean is “you are not that special”. I think this is the first step towards a better version of yourself, There’s a sea of people more talented and committed than you and that’s okay that’s just life that’s just life (yep it’s a ‘sound of the metal’ reference). I also started to realize the consequences of my actions and taking responsibility for them, You see when I first started universities I thought I’ll never need to study hard and that was something I  left in  high school and I couldn’t have been more wrong. In my first semester I failed two courses namely “Calculus 1” and “Basics of Mathematics” this was a shock for me but it was deserved and also needed. I thought that I’ll repeat that year because these were the easiest courses according to senior students (and common sense ), but I changed my attitude and made a promise to myself that this won’t happen and it didn’t, but I learned things the hard way. In the end the way I look back at it is if I somehow managed to pass first year with that attitude and mentality I would’ve repeated the following -much harder- year(s) so you can say that it was for the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third thing is that  its courses are not as outdated as most of students think. What I mean is for the core courses most of the concepts taught are standard and the same concepts are and will taught for years even in the best universities, let’s just say that they are taught very poorly (I’ll elaborate on this in the following section). computer science courses are particularly a good example of this. 
Wish I could add more good things about you school of math, but I think that’s all I have in your defense right now (maybe in a future version of this post I’ll be able to come up with more).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;now-to-my-favorite-part-the-negative-things&quot;&gt;Now to my favorite part the negative things:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think one of the most annoying things I had to deal with was that almost all of the professors in all of the courses didn’t care to provide any sense of intuitive understanding of the concepts they taught before diving into the mathematical formulas in other words they confused definition with intuition.
In my opinion the process should be as follows the intuition -&amp;gt; the real world applications of it -&amp;gt; the math behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve met graduates who couldn’t even answer a question like :why we need a standard deviation when have a variance? don’t they both measure the same thing? or even simpler what’s integral actually means? and why is it the opposite of differentiation.
I’m thinking about making a whole series of posts about concepts that I think are  more interesting than I thought  and should’ve been taught better but I think Grant sanderson is doing better than I’ll ever be able to in this regard. If you interested in math I highly recommend you subscribe to his YouTube channel “3Blue1Brown”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second thing is the lack of practical and hands on experience. If I said that most of  students reach their final years without a single technical skill, I won’t be  wrong. Most of the assignments and small projects get copied from the internet or previous years projects. The sad thing is that they (the students) actually get used to this, so in their final year project or even worse when they start to work in a real job they struggle a lot especially in the implementation part of it. All of this is a result of the professors making passing the exams more important than actually gaining knowledge and understanding the ideas behind these courses. I myself got A’s in some courses that I honestly didn’t believe I would pass them even, but that all because of the broken academic system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third thing actually has more to do with the students themselves which is the lack of active community that helps provide what’s missing of the whole learning process compared to other faculties. To be fair there were several attempts to establish such communities like “Briding the gap” and  “SSE” but all of them suffered from the same problem: they were all based on the personal effort of few certain individuals which meant whenever these individuals were unavailable for whatever reasons the whole thing stops in its tracks. A more recent but promising one is “FMS students association” which is still to early to be judged but I believe that it has the  potentials to achieve higher level than its predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like I’ve side tracked a little bit of my point in this post, but it’s hard to write down a summary of 7 years in one post anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link to : &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E0J2LObdT-g&quot;&gt;Advice to undergraduates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;link to: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCYO_jab_esuFRV4b17AJtAw&quot;&gt;3Blue1Brown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;see you next week (probably).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">What I’ve learned from my undergrad years “A university is a collection of buildings where in exchange for all your time, money, and dignity you’ll get rewarded with a clammy hand shake, some paper with special ribbon on it, and a life time of crippling social regrets.” This is the opening statement of one of my favorite YouTube videos (I’ll leave a link to it below) I think it’s a good start this post. Now that I’m at my last semester of college, I find myself thinking a lot about my whole academic life. Few days ago friend of mine was singing a songs which lyrics translates to “All of this was for what “ even thought the context is completely different I started to think: “of what use where all of this courses?” “Will I ever need the informations I learned in that year?”, “What are the real life applications for that concept? why did I even bother with it”. In this post I’ll try to summarize my thoughts about my years in college, and what was good and what was not.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reasons That your progress is not as you want</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/02/progress.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reasons That your progress is not as you want" /><published>2021-08-02T02:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-02T02:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/02/progress</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/02/progress.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through my journey between web devolopment and data science I’ve wasted so much time, effort and resources without actuchlly leveling up my skills, I have always found my self in this limbo of being way better than a beginner and yet far from a profissonal.
Now even though I’m no where near my goals for my progress in data science (which is my main interest currently) but taking note of these shortcomings of my learning journey is really helping me to be more productive. So the goal of this post is to help others save precious time that I wasted, so let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;youre-doing-the-opposite-of-less-is-more&quot;&gt;You’re doing the opposite of “less is more”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1614555281536-6755500b7494?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=1934&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;less is more&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always liked this qoute the first time I knew about it was when I was reading about linux commands and the “less” was used to show the contents of a file therefore more of that file, “but what does this have to do with me not making progress” you might rightfully ask, well the my first advice is to work with as LESS learning resources as possible (courses, books, blog posts,…ect) this might seem counterintuitive at first but if you’re anything like me (a person who litterly wants to know everything at the same time),you might find yourself very distracted with tons of courses you’ll never finish and PDFs you never really read.
So the best advice I can give you is to not do more than one course or a book simultaneously this will make you understand details better and you will not feel rushed to finish it for the sake of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;youre-comparing-between-technologies&quot;&gt;You’re comparing between technologies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is it Python or R, Tensorflow or Pytorch, React or Angular or Vue, bla bla bla this is the most useless conversation or web search you’ll ever make, But believe it or not this kind of things really wast a lot of time becuase they will discourge you and get you to switch in the middle of the road. Recentlly I’ve come across a tweet by francios chollet (the creator of keras) which really summries my whole point here perfectlly “The best programming language is the one you know well and enjoy using. The one  that makes you feel productive.”. so next time when you have this kind of thoughs try to think about “what” are you making and the “How” part will be easier and clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1464374288807-174911d4adb9?ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=336&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;less is more&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-think-you-can-master-it-in-short-time-with-little-effort&quot;&gt;You think you can master it in short time with little effort&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now you might start to see the pattern or what all of this have in common “The search for short cuts” this is your enemy  I remember when  watching “requim for a dream”  the first time and thought it’s about how bad drugs are but then I read that the director darren aronofsky said that the film actully has nothing to do about that, instead it’s about the sequences of trying to cheat your way through life. I won’t spoil the film here but i think you’ll get the idea. when you try to finish more books and courses (or any other resources maybe series of blogs or articls) you’re doing the same, your goal changes from gaining knowledge and skills to finish this as fast as possible.
Sorry to break it down for you but there no way you can gain skills without continuous effort. to be good at things you have to be consistant, displined and patient otherwise you’re cheating yourself and wasting your time. binge watching tutorials and courses will not make you a CTO.
&lt;!-- 
&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1614555281536-6755500b7494?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1934&amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;less is more&quot; width=&quot;600&quot;/&gt; --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;youre-hands-are-not-dirty-enough&quot;&gt;you’re Hands are not dirty enough&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We  learn by example and by direct experience because there are limits to the adequacy of verbal instruction.”-Malcom Gladwell. You have to extend upon the knowledge you gain from different sources for example if you’re watching a course about web devolopment and the instructor is making a simple Todo web app, one thing you can do is to try to add more functionallty to it, you can add a login and registration options so different users can have different todos maybe try to get the app to send notificatons to the users email or phone there’s a lot of other cool things to add even for a small project like this. My point here is you have to be brave enough to try and implement you own crazy ideas that’s the only way you can be confident in your technical skills, and confidance is way more important than any other skill another qoute I really like is “We learn through direct experience; to accept a theory without experience it is to learn nothing at all”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1494660251519-9845cdb85fc3?ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=715&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;less is more&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;youre-afraid-of-looking-stupid&quot;&gt;You’re afraid of looking stupid&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every master was once a beginner, but we humans really care too much about our status and our ego can sometimes be our greatest enemy. to overcame this think about babies, (yes these little human ) they come to this world with zero knowledge about any thing and how do they learn? they don’t care or worry about looking stupid or silly, they simply try to mimic  actions they saw from their family in there own and keep trying until they master every single human skills from crawling to walking to speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1571211468362-33f20cb1982f?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=334&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;less is more&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;youre-doing-it-alone&quot;&gt;You’re doing it alone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This related to the previous point, what is the best way to not look stupid or ignorant ? don’t show your work to others but it’s almost always a grandteed way to make poor progress. you think you don’t need anyone everything is on the internet one click away right ? why bother risking being judged and looking stupid asking people for adivce. This actuclly has some truth in it but mainly for techical problems sure you can find the  soluation to  any technical problem in the internet but, your learning journey consist of more than just that there will be moments of stress, doubt and might even feel lost in the plethora of technologies and career paths. In such case having a mentor or anyone who share the same intrests as you do comes really handy.
Try to reach out to as many people as possible in your area of intrest this will make your learnig journey more enjoyable. You might be suprised by how many similar minded people went throught similar problem you’re facing now which makes solving them easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1516321497487-e288fb19713f?ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=750&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;less is more&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first real post in this blog I hope you enjoyed this post and found it useful, feel free to reach out to me if you have any comments. I’ll try to publish this posts more often.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">Background Through my journey between web devolopment and data science I’ve wasted so much time, effort and resources without actuchlly leveling up my skills, I have always found my self in this limbo of being way better than a beginner and yet far from a profissonal. Now even though I’m no where near my goals for my progress in data science (which is my main interest currently) but taking note of these shortcomings of my learning journey is really helping me to be more productive. So the goal of this post is to help others save precious time that I wasted, so let’s get started. You’re doing the opposite of “less is more”</summary></entry></feed>