<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-09-02T16:58:22+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Raheem’s Blog</title><subtitle>My Opiniones on things and stuff</subtitle><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><entry><title type="html">Tidyverse For A Messy Mind</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/01/tidyverse-intro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tidyverse For A Messy Mind" /><published>2021-09-01T14:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-09-01T14:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/01/tidyverse-intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/09/01/tidyverse-intro.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-journey-with-r&quot;&gt;My Journey With R&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first started to learn about machine learning and data science it didn’t make any sense for me to learn any other language than python 
It’s easy to learn and code in,
Requires minimum installations of other programs so you can get started quickly, has a library for almost every thing I needed,  and I already had some experience in it from my web development days (back when I was using Django framework) so learning something like R seemed redundant and  unnecessary so I never really cared about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I  didn’t think about R again until my fourth year in college when there was a course on applied statistics which used to be taught in stata and other statistical packages, but lucky for us I think we were the first or second batch to be taught R and I recall that there was some conflicts between the students on which language should be used in the course Python or R, and even though - as I recall- the majority voted for python we were still taught R which turned out to be pretty cool actully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I  won’t lie at first R didn’t seem to offer much more or any thing new because we were studying the basics of the language (variables definitions,  for loops , functions, etc…) and  I was studying it for an exam only (it was the easiest A+ ever by the way), but as always I wish I was told how useful it’s going to be and how important was it to dive deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never opened Rstudio for months after that until the next semester when I had some code assignments in R for time series analysis and survival time analysis courses when I looked through the time series textbook  I was amazed by the beautiful plots and even more surprised by how little R code they used to generate this beautiful plots and so I found out about ggplot package which is a R package for plotting based on the “grammar of graphics” (a layered approach to plotting and visualization) which then lead me to discover the tidyverse packages and Shiny web apps and it was so awesome I wanted to re-learn everything I learned before in Python again in R.
One of the best things I found was the #TidyTuesday challenge on Twitter which is a weekly challenge where people form all over the R community try their data visualization and data analysis techniques on one specific dataset for that week .
You can find a very insightful submissions and some people sometimes share their code and steps it’s really very helpful community. Every week I want to participate in #TidyTuesday but I always forget or just get lazy and procrastinate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being exposed to all of this at the same time felt so overwhelming I literally didn’t know were to start, but learning from my previous mistakes I wanted to learn with minimal resources and because R is so amazing there’s a lot of data to play with and experiment on that comes with R and additonal datasets once you install tidyverse package and so I started to mess around, this turned out to be useful when we had to make a project for the design of experiments course, becuase I didn’t like SPSS graphs and ggplot made the project look much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-i-like-about-tidyverse&quot;&gt;What i like about tidyverse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tidyverse according to thier offical website is “The tidyverse is an opinionated collection of R packages designed for data science. All packages share an underlying design philosophy, grammar, and data structures.” and this meant that it’s so intuitive to use the functions names and the overall work flow becomes much easier, but the real game changer is the pipe operator &lt;em&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/em&gt; (a fancier and more recent version is |&amp;gt; it’s not fully adoptedyet) this enables you to chain functions together so the output of one function is the input of the other. This meant you can easily implement a pipeline that reads the data , cleans it (remove null values, impute missing value, drop unimportant columns, etc), then does some filtering and grouping and Finally plotting a beautiful graph, and all of this in one line. Tidyverse made me understand why so many programmers now days prefier functional programming paradigm: much cleaner code easier to implement, test and debug. I’m a lazy person I would like to get as many things done with as few steps as possible tidyverse gives me just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing is the whole  community is so helpful (I already said that but it’s worth repeating) you can find very creative solutions to most of your errors and problems and there’s always new updates and new helpful packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-note&quot;&gt;Final Note&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t want this post to be understood as a comparison between R and Python as I said before I hate comparing technologies 
If you love Python and you feel like everything I said is already available for you in Python in a more convenient way that’s completely fine, but I still think it’s useful to approach things from different perspective, personally I was missing out on a lot of cool things in R. It can actually be beneficial to your Python (or any other language) skills, because similar to learning natural languages learning new one can help you understand the other better. I’ve learned a lot of interesting facts about English after studying Spanish for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of this qoute “from a wider perspective, the tidyverse can be seen as sub-dialect of the R language that is evolving to express ideas and tasks inherent in Data Science workflows and software development. This dialect may not be for everyone, but it does seem to be helping many R fluent data scientists frame their conversations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This  post wasn’t actually meant to be for this week, I was working on something different but it wasn’t ready yet and I didn’t want to lose the momentum. So please excuse me if this seems rushed or short I promise to write more about tidyverse and the most important R packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you interested in learning more I’ll leave this link to this great post &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tidyverse.org/blog/2021/08/teach-tidyverse-2021/&quot;&gt;Teaching the tidyverse in 2021&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you next week!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">My Journey With R When I first started to learn about machine learning and data science it didn’t make any sense for me to learn any other language than python It’s easy to learn and code in, Requires minimum installations of other programs so you can get started quickly, has a library for almost every thing I needed, and I already had some experience in it from my web development days (back when I was using Django framework) so learning something like R seemed redundant and unnecessary so I never really cared about it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I will Stop blogging</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/26/the-end.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I will Stop blogging" /><published>2021-08-26T14:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-26T14:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/26/the-end</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/26/the-end.html">&lt;p&gt;If think this is actually my last blog post then I’m sorry to disappoint you, but I’m not going to stop, at least not for the foreseeable future. Why the drama then? well, I actually thought about quitting before, especially after last post for many reasons, but I reconsidered and decided that I’m not going to. Below I’ll give an explanation to why I thought about stopping this blog, why I changed my mind and when I will really stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reasons-to-stop&quot;&gt;Reasons To Stop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I said many times that the main beneficiary from this blog is me, I still however care about the opinions of the people reading my posts (there’s only about 10 currently) and for some reason there was relatively low feed back especially for the last post and I started thinking the wrong way (like I always do) which is that because how uninteresting they are. I thought “no one asked and no one cares about your opinions, they only interacted with first ones out of pity and now got bored from pretending to care”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason is that I’m a very scattered person who is always obsessed with learning or trying new things (which can be a very bad trait) and between all of this stuff I really want to learn or try blogging is not a priority right? Well no, and I will tell you why in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-will-not&quot;&gt;Why I will not&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all there’s some hidden technical part to this blog for example I have to maintain the code and do some git stuff (basically some commits and pulls and pushs). Also learning something new like markdown which is a more convenient way than html to write posts like this one,  plus This blog is actually made by a Ruby language framework called jekyll ( I never ever wrote a single line in Ruby and probably never will, but am still able to work with it isn’t this amazing ?). These things are not actually complicated, but still in the end they are extra things am learning on the go and they will -hopefully- be useful one day.
Also you might have realized that there’s so many spelling and grammar mistakes and serious lack of fluency (sometimes I forget some words in the middle of a sentence) I never thought about how much I need to improve my writing skills before starting this blog (thanks to you autocorrection), in general, active language skills (speaking and writing) are commonly neglected while learning any language. So to summarize I’m actually learning more about things I didn’t know in addition to the main goal of this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly I have almost always been in similar situations like this, where I go from enthusiasm at the beginning then slowly losing interest until I end up in a half done projects which I completely forgot why I even started it. So this time I want to see things through, I want to know what would happen in the end (if there’s an end to this ) I think had my fair share of (what-if)s so far. Finishing things really improve our mental state since it leaves little to overthink about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-least-comfortable-choice&quot;&gt;The least comfortable choice.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to come up with excuses to give up. The way I thought about this is actually me just being both lazy and coward if you think your content is not good enough you improve it, You don’t just giving up the whole thing. 
I really hope that I’ll be able to do as many uncomfortable things in my life as possible. Almost all of the good things (and people ) require certain level of risk and discomfort at first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-will-i-ever-stop&quot;&gt;When will I ever stop?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I made things clear on why I would keep blogging it’s time to tell you when will I stop. Actually there’s is basically one thing I’m  afraid of becoming which is being fraud. I don’t like pretentious things or people.
There’s a song called “smoke and mirror” by gotye I always feel nervous when listen to it, Because I’m afraid of getting used to people praising my mediocre skills and no I’m not hating on myself here or trying to be humble, but I think that’s they don’t know enough about the things I do to make a good judgment. For example if someone who doesn’t even know what a  web server is kept telling you that you’re a good back-end developer it wouldn’t mean anything to you right ? .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog started to look like a dairy so I’m thinking about making more technical posts next. This makes it 4 out of 4 in august I’m feeling proud actually, might treat myself to an Ice cream or something haha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week midterm will decide if there’s a post or not. Wish me luck !&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">If think this is actually my last blog post then I’m sorry to disappoint you, but I’m not going to stop, at least not for the foreseeable future. Why the drama then? well, I actually thought about quitting before, especially after last post for many reasons, but I reconsidered and decided that I’m not going to. Below I’ll give an explanation to why I thought about stopping this blog, why I changed my mind and when I will really stop.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On The Nature Of Advice</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/20/advices.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On The Nature Of Advice" /><published>2021-08-20T02:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-20T02:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/20/advices</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/20/advices.html">&lt;p&gt;As someone who didn’t like giving or asking for advices, starting a blog where I’m sharing my ideas and opinions might seems like a contradiction, but as I said in the very first post of this blog I’m doing this for my own benefit. whenever I’m writing a new post I’m practically talking to myself, but if someone somehow finds it useful then that’s awesome, but its not my goal to tell people what to do I’m just sharing my thoughts from my humble experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-dont-like-advices&quot;&gt;Why I Don’t Like Advices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I need to make things more clear when I say that I do not like advices. Don’t get me wrong I do believe that sometimes some types of advices  works, I just think that most of “successful” people tend to believe that thier journey is completely replicable when in fact no one’s is. There’s so many examples of very successful people didn’t realize that they were doing the right thing until it eventually paid off  and sometimes they don’t even comprehend how circumstances played in their advantage and how luck can actually determine a lot of your decisions in life. Therefore even when these advices come with good intentions they can lead to serious discouragement and disappointment when they don’t work out well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-one-knows&quot;&gt;No One knows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one know the secrets to success not even great successful people. 
The other day I was reading about Bayesian Statistics and found out that in fact Thomas Bayes who actually came up with the conditional probability equation which we now know as Bayes’s theorem one of the most important theorems in statistics (if not the most ) he never published it because he didn’t think it something of any value in fact it was published after his death and we have Thomas’s friend Richard Price to thank for that, he found it his apartment and arranged it for its posthumous publication (actually while writing this I found this so interesting that it deserves its own whole post). I also remember reading something similar about Franz Kafka the genius novelist who ordered his servant to burn all of his useless mediocre work (in his opinion) after his death, but luckily for humanity his servant didn’t listen to him. 
Some people  just love asking for advices even on obvious things Goerge Hotz the  founder of comma ai (a company that makes self driving cars computers) said this when he was asked about giving advices to this type ofpeople “I will write a self help book and charge 67$ for it then I’m going to write on the very first page of this book: ‘all of this advices are meaningless but you gonna be sucker and buy it anyway’” I loved his answer because sometimes people wants to be told advices just because it would make them feel better about themselves they’ll think just by seeking advices they’re already better people which is nice way to think about yourself I guess, but can be very misleading or even harmful on the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the only type of advices you can actually give are either technical or very specific where you almost giving instructions. You can’t give advice for someone who asks “how can I learn X ?” I don’t know, Google it ? “how can I be good at Y” do it a lot maybe. These types of questions are annoying, I mean a lot of things in this life just kind of work out, you should stop wasting your time looking for advices and short cuts you’ll end up waste more time. If someone would ask me how i managed to get good exam score in a certain course I’d probably tell them to ware blue shirt on the day of the exam, because I remember doing better in exams when I ware blue shirts. This actually as relevant as telling them to study hard or telling them not to skip lectures. I think deep down they know exactly what they should do and what they are really after is the sense of reassurance that comes from people giving us advices because at the end what is an advice anyway? I like to define it as: the best guess to how thinks actually work out to best case scenario (or any good enough scenario that made people ask you for advices )” it’s basically like saying things will be fine if you do this which is something you just cann’t guarantee, “guess” is the  keyword here you never know what really happened. I think you can actually tell a lot about people just by how comfortable they’re with saying “I don’t know”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that my view on this topic is bit exreme and biased maybe because of the many advices that were useless or because of all the times I did the oppiste of what I was told and  things turned out very good. Maybe this whole post will be awkward if one I publish a book or give a talk at some event in which I’m baisclly telling people advices, but who knows maybe I look back at this post few years from now and I’ll feel  proud that I changed the way I think about this. 
Finally if I had to give someone one piece of advice it would definitely be “do not listen to me”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I don’t publish another post next week I’ll probably wont for a long time even though I actually have some drafts for a few more posts but I’m expecting a busy schedule next month so maybe no new post till October.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">As someone who didn’t like giving or asking for advices, starting a blog where I’m sharing my ideas and opinions might seems like a contradiction, but as I said in the very first post of this blog I’m doing this for my own benefit. whenever I’m writing a new post I’m practically talking to myself, but if someone somehow finds it useful then that’s awesome, but its not my goal to tell people what to do I’m just sharing my thoughts from my humble experience.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What I’ve learned from my undergrad years</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/12/undergradute.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What I’ve learned from my undergrad years" /><published>2021-08-12T02:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-12T02:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/12/undergradute</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/12/undergradute.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-ive-learned-from-my-undergrad-years&quot;&gt;What I’ve learned from my undergrad years&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“A university is a collection of buildings where in exchange for all your time, money,  and dignity you’ll get rewarded with a clammy hand shake, some paper with special ribbon on it, and a life time of crippling social regrets.”&lt;/em&gt; This is the opening statement of one of my favorite YouTube videos (I’ll leave a link to it below) I think it’s a good start this post.
Now that I’m at my last semester of college, I find myself thinking a lot about my whole academic life. Few days ago friend of mine was singing a songs which lyrics translates to “All of this was for what “ even thought the context is completely different I started to think: “of what use where all of this courses?” “Will I ever need the informations I learned in that year?”, “What are the real life applications for that concept? why did I even bother with it”. 
In this post I’ll try to summarize my thoughts about my years in college, and what was good and what was not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-lets-start-with-the-good-things&quot;&gt;First let’s start with the good things:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be frank not many of them can be said when we’re talking about my college, but I still can’t say there was none.
I think the best thing for me was that the fact that there’s a lot of people to look up to. I’m talking about alumni that are now working in the biggest tech companies in the world (Google,  Facebook,..)in very exciting careers or doing their post grad studies in leading universities, and they managed to do it in “relatively” short time. These kind of people really gives me hope that if I work hard enough and with little luck great things might happen to me too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think another good thing I learned is to accept my mediocrity. Don’t get me wrong I still do believe that we should try to be better every single day, but what I mean is “you are not that special”. I think this is the first step towards a better version of yourself, There’s a sea of people more talented and committed than you and that’s okay that’s just life that’s just life (yep it’s a ‘sound of the metal’ reference). I also started to realize the consequences of my actions and taking responsibility for them, You see when I first started universities I thought I’ll never need to study hard and that was something I  left in  high school and I couldn’t have been more wrong. In my first semester I failed two courses namely “Calculus 1” and “Basics of Mathematics” this was a shock for me but it was deserved and also needed. I thought that I’ll repeat that year because these were the easiest courses according to senior students (and common sense ), but I changed my attitude and made a promise to myself that this won’t happen and it didn’t, but I learned things the hard way. In the end the way I look back at it is if I somehow managed to pass first year with that attitude and mentality I would’ve repeated the following -much harder- year(s) so you can say that it was for the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third thing is that  its courses are not as outdated as most of students think. What I mean is for the core courses most of the concepts taught are standard and the same concepts are and will taught for years even in the best universities, let’s just say that they are taught very poorly (I’ll elaborate on this in the following section). computer science courses are particularly a good example of this. 
Wish I could add more good things about you school of math, but I think that’s all I have in your defense right now (maybe in a future version of this post I’ll be able to come up with more).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;now-to-my-favorite-part-the-negative-things&quot;&gt;Now to my favorite part the negative things:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think one of the most annoying things I had to deal with was that almost all of the professors in all of the courses didn’t care to provide any sense of intuitive understanding of the concepts they taught before diving into the mathematical formulas in other words they confused definition with intuition.
In my opinion the process should be as follows the intuition -&amp;gt; the real world applications of it -&amp;gt; the math behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve met graduates who couldn’t even answer a question like :why we need a standard deviation when have a variance? don’t they both measure the same thing? or even simpler what’s integral actually means? and why is it the opposite of differentiation.
I’m thinking about making a whole series of posts about concepts that I think are  more interesting than I thought  and should’ve been taught better but I think Grant sanderson is doing better than I’ll ever be able to in this regard. If you interested in math I highly recommend you subscribe to his YouTube channel “3Blue1Brown”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second thing is the lack of practical and hands on experience. If I said that most of  students reach their final years without a single technical skill, I won’t be  wrong. Most of the assignments and small projects get copied from the internet or previous years projects. The sad thing is that they (the students) actually get used to this, so in their final year project or even worse when they start to work in a real job they struggle a lot especially in the implementation part of it. All of this is a result of the professors making passing the exams more important than actually gaining knowledge and understanding the ideas behind these courses. I myself got A’s in some courses that I honestly didn’t believe I would pass them even, but that all because of the broken academic system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third thing actually has more to do with the students themselves which is the lack of active community that helps provide what’s missing of the whole learning process compared to other faculties. To be fair there were several attempts to establish such communities like “Briding the gap” and  “SSE” but all of them suffered from the same problem: they were all based on the personal effort of few certain individuals which meant whenever these individuals were unavailable for whatever reasons the whole thing stops in its tracks. A more recent but promising one is “FMS students association” which is still to early to be judged but I believe that it has the  potentials to achieve higher level than its predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like I’ve side tracked a little bit of my point in this post, but it’s hard to write down a summary of 7 years in one post anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link to : &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E0J2LObdT-g&quot;&gt;Advice to undergraduates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;link to: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCYO_jab_esuFRV4b17AJtAw&quot;&gt;3Blue1Brown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;see you next week (probably).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">What I’ve learned from my undergrad years “A university is a collection of buildings where in exchange for all your time, money, and dignity you’ll get rewarded with a clammy hand shake, some paper with special ribbon on it, and a life time of crippling social regrets.” This is the opening statement of one of my favorite YouTube videos (I’ll leave a link to it below) I think it’s a good start this post. Now that I’m at my last semester of college, I find myself thinking a lot about my whole academic life. Few days ago friend of mine was singing a songs which lyrics translates to “All of this was for what “ even thought the context is completely different I started to think: “of what use where all of this courses?” “Will I ever need the informations I learned in that year?”, “What are the real life applications for that concept? why did I even bother with it”. In this post I’ll try to summarize my thoughts about my years in college, and what was good and what was not.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reasons That your progress is not as you want</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/02/progress.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reasons That your progress is not as you want" /><published>2021-08-02T02:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-02T02:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/02/progress</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/08/02/progress.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through my journey between web devolopment and data science I’ve wasted so much time, effort and resources without actuchlly leveling up my skills, I have always found my self in this limbo of being way better than a beginner and yet far from a profissonal.
Now even though I’m no where near my goals for my progress in data science (which is my main interest currently) but taking note of these shortcomings of my learning journey is really helping me to be more productive. So the goal of this post is to help others save precious time that I wasted, so let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;youre-doing-the-opposite-of-less-is-more&quot;&gt;You’re doing the opposite of “less is more”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1614555281536-6755500b7494?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=1934&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;less is more&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always liked this qoute the first time I knew about it was when I was reading about linux commands and the “less” was used to show the contents of a file therefore more of that file, “but what does this have to do with me not making progress” you might rightfully ask, well the my first advice is to work with as LESS learning resources as possible (courses, books, blog posts,…ect) this might seem counterintuitive at first but if you’re anything like me (a person who litterly wants to know everything at the same time),you might find yourself very distracted with tons of courses you’ll never finish and PDFs you never really read.
So the best advice I can give you is to not do more than one course or a book simultaneously this will make you understand details better and you will not feel rushed to finish it for the sake of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;youre-comparing-between-technologies&quot;&gt;You’re comparing between technologies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is it Python or R, Tensorflow or Pytorch, React or Angular or Vue, bla bla bla this is the most useless conversation or web search you’ll ever make, But believe it or not this kind of things really wast a lot of time becuase they will discourge you and get you to switch in the middle of the road. Recentlly I’ve come across a tweet by francios chollet (the creator of keras) which really summries my whole point here perfectlly “The best programming language is the one you know well and enjoy using. The one  that makes you feel productive.”. so next time when you have this kind of thoughs try to think about “what” are you making and the “How” part will be easier and clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1464374288807-174911d4adb9?ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=336&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;less is more&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-think-you-can-master-it-in-short-time-with-little-effort&quot;&gt;You think you can master it in short time with little effort&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now you might start to see the pattern or what all of this have in common “The search for short cuts” this is your enemy  I remember when  watching “requim for a dream”  the first time and thought it’s about how bad drugs are but then I read that the director darren aronofsky said that the film actully has nothing to do about that, instead it’s about the sequences of trying to cheat your way through life. I won’t spoil the film here but i think you’ll get the idea. when you try to finish more books and courses (or any other resources maybe series of blogs or articls) you’re doing the same, your goal changes from gaining knowledge and skills to finish this as fast as possible.
Sorry to break it down for you but there no way you can gain skills without continuous effort. to be good at things you have to be consistant, displined and patient otherwise you’re cheating yourself and wasting your time. binge watching tutorials and courses will not make you a CTO.
&lt;!-- 
&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1614555281536-6755500b7494?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1934&amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;less is more&quot; width=&quot;600&quot;/&gt; --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;youre-hands-are-not-dirty-enough&quot;&gt;you’re Hands are not dirty enough&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We  learn by example and by direct experience because there are limits to the adequacy of verbal instruction.”-Malcom Gladwell. You have to extend upon the knowledge you gain from different sources for example if you’re watching a course about web devolopment and the instructor is making a simple Todo web app, one thing you can do is to try to add more functionallty to it, you can add a login and registration options so different users can have different todos maybe try to get the app to send notificatons to the users email or phone there’s a lot of other cool things to add even for a small project like this. My point here is you have to be brave enough to try and implement you own crazy ideas that’s the only way you can be confident in your technical skills, and confidance is way more important than any other skill another qoute I really like is “We learn through direct experience; to accept a theory without experience it is to learn nothing at all”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1494660251519-9845cdb85fc3?ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=715&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;less is more&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;youre-afraid-of-looking-stupid&quot;&gt;You’re afraid of looking stupid&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every master was once a beginner, but we humans really care too much about our status and our ego can sometimes be our greatest enemy. to overcame this think about babies, (yes these little human ) they come to this world with zero knowledge about any thing and how do they learn? they don’t care or worry about looking stupid or silly, they simply try to mimic  actions they saw from their family in there own and keep trying until they master every single human skills from crawling to walking to speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1571211468362-33f20cb1982f?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=334&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;less is more&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;youre-doing-it-alone&quot;&gt;You’re doing it alone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This related to the previous point, what is the best way to not look stupid or ignorant ? don’t show your work to others but it’s almost always a grandteed way to make poor progress. you think you don’t need anyone everything is on the internet one click away right ? why bother risking being judged and looking stupid asking people for adivce. This actuclly has some truth in it but mainly for techical problems sure you can find the  soluation to  any technical problem in the internet but, your learning journey consist of more than just that there will be moments of stress, doubt and might even feel lost in the plethora of technologies and career paths. In such case having a mentor or anyone who share the same intrests as you do comes really handy.
Try to reach out to as many people as possible in your area of intrest this will make your learnig journey more enjoyable. You might be suprised by how many similar minded people went throught similar problem you’re facing now which makes solving them easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1516321497487-e288fb19713f?ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=750&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;less is more&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first real post in this blog I hope you enjoyed this post and found it useful, feel free to reach out to me if you have any comments. I’ll try to publish this posts more often.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">Background Through my journey between web devolopment and data science I’ve wasted so much time, effort and resources without actuchlly leveling up my skills, I have always found my self in this limbo of being way better than a beginner and yet far from a profissonal. Now even though I’m no where near my goals for my progress in data science (which is my main interest currently) but taking note of these shortcomings of my learning journey is really helping me to be more productive. So the goal of this post is to help others save precious time that I wasted, so let’s get started. You’re doing the opposite of “less is more”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Let The Journey Begin</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/07/15/first-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let The Journey Begin" /><published>2021-07-15T02:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-15T02:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/07/15/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/07/15/first-post.html">&lt;p&gt;As someone Who has enjoyed a lot of great content made by awesome people online I've always wanted to  not only contirbute and give back, but also to create the type of content that I think is not available in the the way that it shoud be.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been thinking of starting a blog for a quite long time now but I just couldn't find the time and the ideas to get started. Now (unlike most of my other ideas) this may actully see the light&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;The Goal Of This Blog&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cann't say that my goals for this blog are clear yet, but mainly this blog will be like a place to throw my random thoughts in. Mainly in topics related to data science, machine learning, and other random topics in CS in general&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is like the &quot;Hello world&quot; of blogging I'm very excited writing it right now even though it does not contian any valuable informations.
    Jeff Delaney (the creator of &quot;fireship.io&quot; one of my faviurate youtube channels and a huge inspration for me) once said:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;The best time to create a youtube channel was ten years ago, the second best time is now!&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That can be generlized on internet blogs as well. In a world filled with so many resource online this might seem redundent and useless, but I'm actully doing this for me in the first place i beleive that I will be the one who benfit the most from this even though I'm hoping that this random thoughts i post  can be of any use for a random strangers on the internet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Final Words&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has only been a test of this whole blogging test I'm still thinking about what would be the first real topic im going to write about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1516414447565-b14be0adf13e?ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=666&amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;Demo Image&quot;&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;To go places and do things that have never been done before – that’s what living is all about.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I just realized how horrable my writing skills are, but let's hope that this can improve along the way lol.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Photographs by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">As someone Who has enjoyed a lot of great content made by awesome people online I've always wanted to not only contirbute and give back, but also to create the type of content that I think is not available in the the way that it shoud be.</summary></entry></feed>