<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-11-01T07:00:37+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Raheem’s Blog</title><subtitle>My Opiniones on things and stuff</subtitle><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><entry><title type="html">November</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/01/November.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="November" /><published>2023-11-01T04:45:13+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-01T04:45:13+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/11/01/November</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/01/November.html"><![CDATA[<p>I think November is one of the least remarkable months of the year, Personally I do not remember a siginficant event in my life that happen in it.</p>]]></content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I think November is one of the least remarkable months of the year, Personally I do not remember a siginficant event in my life that happen in it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spoils Of War</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/09/16/spoils-of-war.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spoils Of War" /><published>2023-09-16T11:45:13+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-16T11:45:13+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/09/16/spoils-of-war</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/09/16/spoils-of-war.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="spoils-of-war">Spoils of war</h1>

<p>Similar to other millions of Sudanese my life changed drastically after April 15th 2023. I’ve lost everything my house, my car, my job and I’m thousands of miles away from my family in a foreign country.</p>

<p>The terrors of this war do not require me to speak further about them. the atrocities committed by the RSF left the whole world shocked not just Sudanese people. But as you might have guessed from the title of this post I’m going to talk about the positive things that I learned or happened to me during this series of unfortunate events.</p>

<h3 id="im-way-stronger-than-i-could-have-ever-imagined">I’m way stronger than I could have ever imagined</h3>

<p>Days without water, electricity, internet connection have been the norm for many residents of Khartoum (and even other states). Along with my family we fled to our home town in Aljazeera state about 80km south of Khartoum, our house there wasn’t a 5 star hotel of course but we are extremely lucky to have a “spare” house that we could live in. I spent days without electricity, fastest internet connection was in kilo bytes if you were patient enough to stay up all night long to use it, for many days I forgot the taste of cold water. while this was happening all I did was wondering how did I ever had the audacity to complain previously about anything in my life but also I was surprised by how much adaptable I was to the whole situation, sure not having an alternative solution back then helped but still I realized how much of our inability to do things or bear any conditions was due to our own mentality.</p>

<h3 id="i-found-peace-in-losing-all-hope">“I found peace in losing all hope”</h3>

<p>Losing Hope, I know that this seems like a negative thing but losing hope in things that holding you back can be one of the most liberating things ever “only after we’ve lost everything we are free to do anything” war destroyed every comfort zone I had before in life making it easier for me to take on harder challenges and choose harder decisions.</p>

<h3 id="زايلة-و-زايل-نعيمكي">“زايلة و زايل نعيمكي”</h3>

<p>Life is ultimately a zero sum game you have nothing to gain and truly nothing to lose. Nothing last forever and whatever is it that you work so hard for in this life can be easily taken away from you without your permission, without you seeing it coming and without it being your fault.</p>

<h3 id="control-is-an-illusion">Control Is An Illusion</h3>

<p>We tend to think that we are in complete control over our life, our hard-work will get us so far in life, we get things because we deserve them, good things will happen to us because we are good people, and the truth is that none of these is actually true, the worst day or the best day of your life could be around the corner and you wouldn’t even know it or predict it let alone trying to control when or where or with whom it might be. Of course I’m not downplaying the importance of hard-working -if this what you understood from reading this then please stop reading- I’m just saying we should stop the wishful thinking that’s all, basically do your best and be ready for the worst because that’s life.</p>

<h3 id="i-love-sudan">I love Sudan</h3>

<p>I love Sudan and I really love it more than I thought I’d ever do as far as I could remember I wanted to leave Sudan and establish a new life for me away from everyone I know, now this is actually happening I don’t find it as rewarding as I thought it would be. I desperately want to get my old life back, I want to go back to Sudan and I want to spend my life working towards making it a better home for future generations. No matter how many years I spend outside of Sudan or which nationality I can get, there’s an ultimate truth that is I will always be Sudanese and I wish that one day far down the line people would be proud of this instead of feeling that it’s just a bad luck for them. If I could meaningfully contribute to that then that’s it for me.</p>

<h3 id="im-a-good-digital-painter-now">I’m a good digital painter now!</h3>

<p>Not all these “spoils” are philosophical some are tangible things I gained from this war, one of which was improving my painting skills, I have been practicing more consistently during the past months and it was so satisfying to watch my skills grow and finally have confidence in my skills and I can now paint faster using my own unique styles and techniques, honestly this was my sole goal since I got into drawing and painting this is literally a life long dream to acquire this skill. All that was possible because of the time this war has given me by taking away things that had more priority in my life, so it’s good to see some light in all of this darkness.</p>

<p>Spoils of war is the 4th episode of season 7 of Game of Thrones, it’s also the name of one the best sound tracks in this show and I liked it so much it was only fitting to make it the title of this post.</p>]]></content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Spoils of war]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Back on Track</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/08/13/comeback.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Back on Track" /><published>2023-08-13T11:45:13+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T11:45:13+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/08/13/comeback</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/08/13/comeback.html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="hello-friend">Hello Friend</h3>
<p>Frist of all it really does feel good to be back writing these posts, it feels like the last time I did this was years ago, I even started to forget how write, build and maintain the github repo. It’s been two years since I decided to start doing this and man what a great descion was it! throughout the time when I couldn’t publish new posts I read most of my old posts and I really felt a lot of different emotions from laughing at how I was stressed about my graduation project to feeling sad remember some special moments and people who were crucial to my journey with this blog but now we don’t even talk.</p>

<h3 id="again-time-flies">Again Time Flies</h3>
<p>Since 2018 and it’s almost like time has been going faster than ever, I cloud swear that all of 202X seems like one long year, so much happened wars, pandamics, coups …etc. And now 2024 is in like 4 months.</p>

<h3 id="new-city-new-world-new-life">New City, New World, New Life</h3>
<p>Like many of Sudanese People I left Sudan after the war broke out, I moved to dubai 3 weeks ago, it’s funny I arrived here on the same day I was here 2 years ago, once as a tourist and now a refugee life is really weird and unexpected.
Hopefully I’ll be able to find some stability and kick-off my career again in a new environment, but it’s quite tough for someone without many years of experience yet I’m still confident that I will be able to make the best out of my situation.</p>

<p>So see you around soon (hopefully), this was just me saying hi and gaining momentoum to get back to blogging I even think about making a substack account what do you think?</p>]]></content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hello Friend Frist of all it really does feel good to be back writing these posts, it feels like the last time I did this was years ago, I even started to forget how write, build and maintain the github repo. It’s been two years since I decided to start doing this and man what a great descion was it! throughout the time when I couldn’t publish new posts I read most of my old posts and I really felt a lot of different emotions from laughing at how I was stressed about my graduation project to feeling sad remember some special moments and people who were crucial to my journey with this blog but now we don’t even talk.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scarcity Of Abundance</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/04/07/scarcity-of-abundance.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scarcity Of Abundance" /><published>2023-04-07T11:45:13+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-07T11:45:13+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/04/07/scarcity-of-abundance</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/04/07/scarcity-of-abundance.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="scarcity-of-abundance">Scarcity Of Abundance</h1>

<p>Ramadan Kareem, everyone! It’s been a long time since I wrote any posts here. I almost forgot how to do this. I’ve only made like four posts in the entirety of 2022 and this is my very first post in 2023 !! but I’m planning to be more productive this year (in what’s left of it). It’s crazy that this blog is 3 months away from being 2 years old, hopefully I’ll relate to this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vyVpRiqOvt4">video</a> some time in the future.</p>

<p>In life, we all have limited resources - whether it’s time, money, or energy. However, it’s not always about having more resources, but using the ones we have effectively. Learning how to make the most of your available resources can help you achieve your goals and live a more fulfilling life.</p>

<h2 id="jack-of-all-trades">Jack Of All Trades</h2>

<p>Since I could remember I was always obsessed with learning new things I wanted to learn everything I came across I wanted to be everything at the same time I wanted to master every track of my field I wanted to be a web developer, graphic designer, data scientist, machine learning engineer, … etc. I wanted to be a “jack of all trades” this in turn led me to spend so much time collecting resources for each of these and spend relatively less time actually learning and improving. If you recognize this pattern or relate to it in some way then you too has suffered from what I like to call scarcity of abundance.</p>

<p>Scarcity is defined as the lack of something but it’s not always generated by the absence of it as I mention in earlier hoarding courses and materials only made my learning outcomes very scarce. But how can one scape this?</p>

<h2 id="prioritizing-your-goals">Prioritizing Your Goals</h2>

<p>One of the most effective ways to make the most of your available resources is to prioritize your goals. By setting clear goals and prioritizing them, you can focus your time, energy, and resources on what matters most.</p>

<p>When you have a clear goal in mind, you can evaluate the importance of each task that requires resources to achieve it. Once you have a clear understanding of the importance of each task, you can make sure your resources are used effectively.</p>

<p>What if prioritizing your goals is also something you don’t know how to do? I’m sorry in that case because that means no one can help you currently as the saying goes “No winds are favorable for a ship without a destination.</p>

<p>Holding on to one thing is hard because of how appealing starting over is, we tend to do this all the time. This is because at the start things are relatively easier but as we get deeper at certain topic naturally  it require more effort so get tempted by the easiness of approaching a different thing and starting over. I think the ability to fight these temptations off are one of the biggest factors on personal success of an individual. This reminds me of one of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OXqkTzyifJQ">my favorite Rick and Morty clip</a></p>

<p>Just an advice if you really don’t what your goals are or what you want to be then you can litrally choose at random just pick up anything and be good at it just like Abraham Lincoln said “whatever you are, be a good one”. What I’ve realized so far is people rarely realize what they really want or even when they do life doesn’t always allow them to fulfil them, you should prioritize your goals yes but also be flexible when life forces you to follow a different order.</p>

<h2 id="reinvent-your-resources">Reinvent Your Resources</h2>

<p>Being resourceful means finding creative ways to achieve your goals using the resources you have. This could mean finding free resources or using resources in new ways.</p>

<p>From a personal experience this has helped me a lot in learning Spanish language I never thought it’s possible to get to the level I got without going a class or having a real instructors. I started my journey with Duolingo it help me with the basics but after that I started adding Spanish content to my content diet I started listinting to spanish songs, spanish movies and series and spanish Youtube channels ( and spanish memes pages ). I was already listning to music and watching youtube but I repurposed it to help learning a new language and proud of the level I got to (nearly B2 ).</p>

<h2 id="remove-clutter">Remove Clutter</h2>

<p>My hate for social media combined with my inability to escape it always makes me feel a bit miserable all the time. We’ve been hacked and hooked by this platforms they changed the neuroplasticity of our brains and made tasks like focusing and paying attention kind of impossible to most people. when was the last time you were able to stay focused for like several hours or even finish a several hours movie in one setting (if your answer is yes then I really congrats you, you are ahead of so many people).</p>

<p>This is the clearest examples of scarcity of abundance we’re drowning in oceans of entertainment yet we are incredibly easily bored, we’re surrounded with people and “friends” and “followers” and yet we feel incredibly lonely, sometimes it makes you think the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/national/longterm/unabomber/manifesto.text.htm">Unabomber</a> had some sense (This is just a joke FBI).</p>

<p>Your brain will try to fight against this but if you blocked these sources of free dopamine; getting things done will get way easier (and even more fun!) remember when the goverment shut down the internet for weeks and then suddenly every one is finishing up books, movies, courses they had ? most people would tell you that it was their most productive time it kind of following the idea of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Region-beta_paradox">region beta</a></p>

<h2 id="seeking-help">Seeking Help</h2>

<p>Seeking help when you need it is another way to make the most of your available resources. Sometimes, we may feel like we have to do everything on our own sense there is a huge of learning resources available online, but this is not always the case.</p>

<p>In fact, I’d like to argue that we can only learn things from others. I’m sorry, but there’s no such thing as “<em>self-learning</em>” Whenever I hear that term, I cringe. Whether you learned from YouTube, by reading books or blogs, or through other means, knowledge and experience have been passed down to you one way or another, even if it’s not in a conventional way. In this age of individualism, where one’s value is directly measured by personal achievements, seeking help may make us look vulnerable or inferior, but it’s actually the normal flow of knowledge.</p>

<p>Having a mentor is one of the best ways to level up in whatever skill you want. If you destroy your ego and break down the barriers, for example, you can reach out to people on LinkedIn and ask for help (yeah, not everything about social media is bad. Why are you looking at me like that?). One thing all competent people have in common is their desire to share knowledge and make it easier for others than it was for them. So, if you ever come across someone who tries to gatekeep knowledge, just know that they’re insecure (rightfully so) about their competence and you’re better off without them.</p>

<p>You know who can also be your mentor ? ChatGPT we really live in that time of human history which is INSANE. I’m going to write a post about this soon.</p>

<h2 id="automating-your-tasks">Automating Your Tasks</h2>

<p>Another way to make the most of your available resources is by automating your tasks. Automating your routine tasks can help you save time and energy that you can use on other important things. There are many tools and apps available that can help you automate your tasks, such as scheduling software, email filters, and social media management tools.</p>

<p>Automating things can help you remove the clutter also by reducing the time you need to interact with different social media and mail services</p>

<h2 id="collaborating-with-others">Collaborating With Others</h2>

<p>Collaborating with others is another way to make the most of your available resources. By working with others, you can combine your resources and achieve your goals more efficiently.</p>

<p>Joining forces with other people doesn’t only save you a lot of time it also makes you benchmark you and validate skills levels more accurately it’s easy to think that we’re left behind or do not have enough skills but when your working with someone and you know how good they are and you see them google the most basic things it kind of sparks some sort of confidence in you that one is expected to know everything all the time and I think in the age ChatGPT and all of these LLMs it’s becoming  more and more important to learn how and what to ask .</p>

<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>

<p>It’s not always about having more resources, but using the ones you have effectively.</p>

<p>Few months ago I made this channel to keep track of books that I found interesting and now I think it has 350+ books and few useful links I only got to read like handful of them but I’m sharing it with you so hopefully you can benefit from it more <a href="https://t.me/+WUcu9zDtNP84OWQ8">here</a></p>

<p><strong><em>“A jack of all trades is a master of none but still (almost) always better than a master of one”</em></strong></p>]]></content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Scarcity Of Abundance]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">IndabaX Sudan 2022</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/11/19/IndabaxSudan2022.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IndabaX Sudan 2022" /><published>2022-11-19T11:45:13+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-19T11:45:13+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/11/19/IndabaxSudan2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/11/19/IndabaxSudan2022.html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="wipes-the-dust-of-this-blog">*wipes the dust of this blog*</h3>

<p>Hello friend, long time no see, I missed writing blogs too, it’s been forever since the last time I uploaded something here which wasn’t intentional lets just say that I’ve been really busy these past couple of months</p>

<hr />
<p>Quick update last time we met here I was working with MTN. Now I’m working at GO digital services as a customer experience executive and I’m loving every part of it. Also I finally got my driving license, something I’ve been trying to get for a long time. Actually another thing is that I also went back to doing digital art and finally bought a drawing tablet.</p>

<p>a lot changed in this year. It’s crazy to talk about so many things for the first time. I think I really pushed myself this year. If someone would’ve told me that I would be able to handle two part-time jobs and one full-time job at the same time and still be able to have a social life and be in contact with my friends and family I honestly wouldn’t believe it. I really think more about my abilities and how to manage time.</p>

<p>Since I’ve decided to go back to blogging and couldn’t really came up with ideas to write about, I decided to write about the most recent interesting thing I’ve been to recently Indabax Sudan 2022.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="what-is-indabax-">What is IndabaX ??</h3>

<p>For those who don’t know, Indaba is an African AI and Machine learning event where experts from around the world gather in one country each year and share their knowledge and stories. The most recent one was in Tunisia. Indabax however is like the local version of the conference where the community of each country organizes a similar event on a smaller scale.</p>

<hr />
<p>I’ve never been to Indaba nor Indabax before (or any other events actually, like in my whole life ) so I was really excited about this one. I want to know a lot of things there here’s the main points I learned from attending Indabax Sudan 2022</p>

<ol>
  <li>There’s quite a big interest from young undergrad students (and from different academic backgrounds too !) in AI, ML and data science so there is actually an audience for this type of educational content.</li>
  <li>There’s a lot of amazing people who are doing great things with AI and ML and a lot of these things can be used in the context of Sudan.</li>
  <li>You can learn a lot and I mean really  a lot about something in one or two days (you won’t be an expert but you can go from zero to grasping the main concepts of something interesting).</li>
  <li>This is not new, however it is worth repeating that networking is a key, you just have to throw yourself out there for the people who share your interest in things you should never underestimate how much this can help you in your life.</li>
</ol>

<p>I really enjoyed the first 2 days of Index this year and can’t wait for the next weekend when the more advanced stuff starts. I also enjoyed getting back to doing this I enjoyed every keystroke of this post.</p>

<p>Hopefully I see you soon,
Goodbye.</p>]]></content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*wipes the dust of this blog*]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy Birthday!!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/07/21/happy-birthday.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy Birthday!!" /><published>2022-07-21T12:45:13+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-21T12:45:13+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/07/21/happy-birthday</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/07/21/happy-birthday.html"><![CDATA[<p>15 july 2021 I wrote my very first post here (https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/07/15/first-post.html)
I can not believe that it’s been a whole year since that day!. I never thought that more than one year later I would be still writing these posts even though I’m not doing it as frequently as I would like to but at least I’m still trying.</p>

<hr />

<p>It’s both terrifying and amazing how fast time is going 
I’ve been through a lot of ups and downs throughout this year, finished school, worked in 3 places and met a lot of amazing new people.</p>

<p>I remember writing about being stressed out about my graduation project which now is a bit nostalgic. I remember my post dreaming about working at tesla or comma ai which helps me remember who I am and what I want and how ambitious I am.</p>

<hr />

<p>I had a small conversation with my friends this weekend about whether it’s better to have a dreams or just live your life not wanting so much and having “reasonable goals” now while that sounds the rational thing to do I really think that you’ll only regret having ambition and big dreams only if you give up on them without trying if you tried and failed then that’s fine that’s just life then or at least this is how I think. I will never regret having a far fetched dream more than I hate the fact I chose the comfortable path and didn’t try even though I’m quite aware I might never achieve what I want.</p>

<p>Looking back now I’m super glad I started this blog really and I already can not wait for next year (if I’m not dead of course ) to see what I would be writing and how I’m thinking about stuff</p>

<p>I want to thank a friend of mine because she was the very first supporter of this blog and I might’ve not started blogging if it wasn’t for her. Thanks Sondus.</p>

<p>I know that in my final post I promised that I would write more frequently but ended up actually disappearing longer and longer. I hate this too but this is what adult life is right?</p>

<p>Hopefully this time I really get back to consistently writing these blog posts at least once a week. Until then, take a slice of the cake and wish this blog a happy birthday.</p>]]></content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[15 july 2021 I wrote my very first post here (https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/07/15/first-post.html) I can not believe that it’s been a whole year since that day!. I never thought that more than one year later I would be still writing these posts even though I’m not doing it as frequently as I would like to but at least I’m still trying.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Seventh Rule Of Fight Club</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/30/the-seventh-rule-of-fight-club.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Seventh Rule Of Fight Club" /><published>2022-05-30T12:45:13+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-30T12:45:13+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/30/the-seventh-rule-of-fight-club</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/30/the-seventh-rule-of-fight-club.html"><![CDATA[<p>I picked this topic today because recently I experienced a lot of pains physically and mentally
two weeks ago I had a horrible toothache and had my tooth extracted I’ve ignored for a while and I do regret that Now.</p>

<p>Also I’m starting to realize that my current job isn’t what I want to be doing for the rest of my life 
And I think by now after 2 months I can make that decision of leaving with higher level of confidence that me leaving is in both sides best interest. I liked it at first, I wanted to give it a chance, but it’s important that one should be true to himself and not compromise about this kind of things although it might be convenient to do so sometimes.
This is what I learned from my toothache. It was easier and more convenient to neglect it for a long time but in the end I experienced so much unnecessary and avoidable pain.</p>

<hr />

<p>The problem with leaving your job is the fear of not being able to land a better one or not having many options. This feeling is inflated with the fact that unfortunately with circumstances out of my hand I already wasted so much time before graduating. I try hard to keep this kind of thoughts from making me settle for a job I don’t like or look forward to.</p>

<p>Thinking about these things while having a toothache is what inspired this post because at that moment I was wondering which one was actually causing me more pain. The toothache is relatively easier to treat and cure obviously, the mental pain is more consistent and profound and harder to cure. I think pain and suffering are essential and unavoidable in life, one should always try to make the most of them and decide which cause or reason he’s willing to suffer for.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="chemical-burn">Chemical Burn</h3>

<p>There’s one scene that always comes to mind when thinking about pain that comes to my mind 
Chemical burn from fight club that scene is one of my favorite scenes of my favorite movie of all time 
When tyler durden poured some chemicals on the narrator hand and  told him that he should face his pain and accept it and not try to escape from it like these scared people do 
And that: 
<i>“It’s only after we’ve lost everything we are free to do anything”</i>.</p>

<p>After a few tries and rejections, self doubts and fears start to magnify and you start to question whether you can afford to achieve your dreams and career goals or you are just destined to work joylessly in something you don’t really like.</p>

<p>For me this is my chemical burn to follow tyler’s advice means I shouldn’t try to shut down this pain I should accept it and acknowledge it and use it to drive myself forward.
I know how easily I can trick myself into believing that things aren’t as bad as they are to delay an uncomfortable decision or  a move.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="seventh-rule-of-fight-club">Seventh rule of fight club</h3>

<p>At this point it might seem like I’m writing this post so that I can talk more about fight club. Most people only remember the first two rules of fight club (which I’m breaking currently obviously) but I find the seventh rule of fight club an interesting one: “Fights will go on as long as they have to” simple as that. I’ll keep fighting for what I want for as long as I’ll have to.</p>

<hr />

<p>This was a very short post. I know I’m trying to gain back some momentum to write more consistently. Let’s hope that the next post will be a celebration of me taking steps in the right direction towards my goals.</p>]]></content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I picked this topic today because recently I experienced a lot of pains physically and mentally two weeks ago I had a horrible toothache and had my tooth extracted I’ve ignored for a while and I do regret that Now.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Path of The Rightous Man</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/22/I-lost-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Path of The Rightous Man" /><published>2022-04-22T04:45:13+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-22T04:45:13+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/22/I-lost-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/22/I-lost-it.html"><![CDATA[<p>“Midway upon the journey of our life, I found myself within a forest dark, for the straightforward pathway had been lost.”</p>

<p>― Dante Alighieri, The Divine Comedy</p>

<hr />

<p>It’s been a while now since I’ve written my last post and a lot of things happened since then.
The idea of me stopping things like blogging and other activities I like for work or because I’m searching for a job have always haunted me but it seems like it’s to some extent unescapable.
I started feeling like Dante at the start of his journey through hell. The hardest thing after graduation is picking your own path but I found out that even when you know where you are going it’s not always enough.</p>

<hr />

<p>Let’s start by a short briefing of how horrible my new year resolution is going in the first quarter of 2022</p>

<p>I can barely pronounce the Russian alphabet (I wanted to challenge myself by learning a language from a different alphabet) regarding my language learning goals
Only 3 times I attempted to try tidytuesday and weren’t even public ones
I’m gaining weight again and almost neglecting all the computer vision tasks and plans
So in short it’s been hard to keep up with it and basiclly a major failure.</p>

<p>Career wise I was snubbed by Go. I felt bad, like really bad because it was a data related job but I also knew that I wasn’t really the best candidate and I didn’t perform well in the technical screening, so their decision was understandable but it still hurts.
Pushed by the desire to get my first job and get the illusion of financial independence I started another job it’s not as technically challenging or data centric as the one from Go but it still worth exploring two weeks in and I still haven’t fully made up my mind about it yet it has its pros and cons so no easy decision here.</p>

<hr />

<p>I now feel lost, I was so naive thinking I wasn’t naive
Like I’ve always known that life is hard and that life after graduation is a lot harder than before it, but I somehow imagined it to be different. Let’s just say I thought it’s going to be hard in a different kind of way. Wishful thinking is of course one of the worst enemies you can have. It’s essentially thinking about things (or sometimes people) the way you wish they are not the way they really are. It can be a career path or it can even be your own abilities.</p>

<p>I don’t know if my current job will lead me to the career I want but then again do I even know what is? that and most importantly do I have what it takes to make it in that career
I think people, especially younger ones, tend to be passionate about their jobs now even though that’s not a bad thing but personally can view a job that way. I don’t think I just want to be one thing in life even though I know I kind of have to in today’s world.</p>

<p>Do I quit next week even though I had no problems so far or just wait and slowly drift away from the path I thought I’m going to walk? 
I should apply for scholarships and leave? then I’ll think about what will happens but that “then” will definitely come and all of this will be repeated but with the stakes being higher 
I don’t want to give up my dreams but sadly I know I might not afford to follow them sometimes you should just settle and realize that it can be luck sometimes that define your life.</p>

<p>also a realization I had recently that if your life has been hard so far that means it’s probably going to get harder and not the oppiset and a lot of people tend to beileve which is like the Monte Carlo fallacy.</p>

<p>I honestly don’t know what to do at this point of my life I feel there’s only bad and worse decisions here</p>

<hr />

<p>“How you can sit there, calmly eating muffins when we are in
this horrible trouble, I can’t make out. You seem to me to be
perfectly heartless.”</p>

<p>“Well, I can’t eat muffins in an agitated manner. The butter
would probably get on my cuffs. One should always eat muffins
quite calmly. It is the only way to eat them.”</p>

<p>“I say it’s perfectly heartless you are eating muffins at all, under
the circumstances.”</p>

<ul>
  <li>Oscar Wilde, The Importance of Being Earnest</li>
</ul>

<p>I like this quote a lot because sometimes all we need is little calmness to make the right decision or at least or lack of calmness and mindfulness leads to even worse decisions so for now I’m just going to try to “eat my muffins” without letting the butter get on my cuffs</p>

<p>And by the way (if you haven’t guess already ) The title of this post comes from pulp fiction one of my all time favorite movies this quote said by jules twice in the movie but when he was explaining  what this made up verse meant in the restaurant scene.</p>

<p>“Ezekiel 25:17. “The path of the righteous man is beset on all sides by the inequities of the selfish and the tyranny of evil men. Blessed is he who, in the name of charity and good will, shepherds the weak through the valley of the darkness. For he is truly his brother’s keeper and the finder of lost children. And I will strike down upon thee with great vengeance and furious anger those who attempt to poison and destroy my brothers. And you will know I am the Lord when I lay my vengeance upon you.”</p>

<p>“…it could be you’re the righteous man and I’m the shepherd and it’s the world that’s evil and selfish. I’d like that. But that shit ain’t the truth. The truth is you’re the weak. And I’m the tyranny of evil men. But I’m tryin, Ringo. I’m tryin’ real hard to be the shepherd.”</p>

<p>I’ve been telling this to myself now that instead of looking at the world as an evil or selfish place it was me who is weak and needs to be stronger.</p>

<p>This is one of my happiest moments of the past few months. I never thought I would miss doing this and the fact that this blog will be 1 year old  in less than 3 months is actually crazy and makes me panic thinking about how fast time is moving.</p>

<p>Hopefully I make another post(s) soon and it won’t take me 3 months to do so.</p>]]></content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Midway upon the journey of our life, I found myself within a forest dark, for the straightforward pathway had been lost.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Abolishing The Educational System</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/22/Abolishing-the-education-system.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Abolishing The Educational System" /><published>2022-02-22T04:45:13+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-22T04:45:13+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/02/22/Abolishing-the-education-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/22/Abolishing-the-education-system.html"><![CDATA[<p>Long time no see I kind of missed my own blog isn’t that sad, but finally I finished college (hopefully that will be official next week) and I was busy with exams, graduation project and another project also I was a part of a mentorship program and I already gave two session so the past two months have been somehow eventful, but still I’d say that it was my laziness and procrastination that prevented me from blogging this whole time.</p>

<hr />
<p>Place a wager on your greed</p>

<p>A wager on your pride</p>

<p>Why try to beat them</p>

<p>When a million tried?</p>

<p>I remember reading this somewhere on George Hotz blog. Since then it has become one of my favorite quotes (I think it’s from a song or something) whenever I’m thinking of doing something that’s basically too much or sounds nuts like “abolishing the education system”. I know I’m not the first to think of this or try to do it but someone has to beat it even if a million tried (and failed).</p>

<p>I’m not an anarchist. I’m not talking about the whole education system at once or preventing people from going to schools, but also I don’t like the fact that this is the de facto of education and people sort of just agreed upon it. It is worthwhile to think about what people consider the normal or the standard way of doing things. Most of the great inventions were just a product of that.</p>

<p>To help you trace back the things that led me to think of this is that at the end of college I just realized how much time and effort can be saved both in the long and the short run simply by adopting smarter methods for education. I’m not exaggerating if I said I’ve learned more than 90% of my courses from YouTube and other websites  and honestly I can see why it’s not possible for someone to get to 100% if given the right guidance which is basically the job of your professors and teachers but that is not happening. Besides, I really hated my college and this is my way of directing these negative feelings towards a good cause.
As a start I genuinely want to fully replace my faculty (fmsi) with an online platform that contains the information, knowledge, resources and method of evaluation for an equivalent of a bachelor degree in math computer science and statistics 
I think these fields are the best start to a much larger change that will make education more efficient, flexible and accessible for all.Computer science courses by nature are the easiest to be completely made online. There’s a plethora of resources already available however for math and statistics that might be harder.
This doesn’t have to be super complex or even useful from the start I won’t let my desire for perfection to hold me from getting started this time similar to this blog it will grow and I’ll try to create the right environment for it to grow</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="thats-not-new-or-original">That’s not new or original</h3>

<p>Originality is overrated 
I think no matter how old an idea is you can still create a lot of new value by improving it and building upon it, doing it better or even by just simply looking at it from a different perspective
Google wasn’t the first search engine 
Facebook wasn’t the first social media 
“Go” was the last ride sharing app to enter the Sudanese market yet all of this examples are the dominant names in their respective fields 
My point is even though there’s a lot of previous efforts to democratize education and make it more available, affordable and overall effective and efficient which is great, I guess there’s still a room for improvement. In this day and age it might seem like everything that can be done has already been done but there’s a simple rule I following regarding creating content and related things which is if you searched for something and didn’t find it online then there’s a chance to create it and benefit from it because there’s a lot of people similar to you that would appreciate it and be excited by it and this is one of the thing that will help me in this project which is the power of the people. I believe that most of the  people who study computer science have learned so much from free online sources and because of that they have the desire to help others the same way.</p>

<h3 id="how-can-you-help-me">How can you help me?</h3>

<p>Literally everyone can help in this  no matter what is your skill and skill level 
I will soon get into more detail, but first I need to know what people think of this, so for now you can spread the word and tell your friends about this and tell me what you think.</p>]]></content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Long time no see I kind of missed my own blog isn’t that sad, but finally I finished college (hopefully that will be official next week) and I was busy with exams, graduation project and another project also I was a part of a mentorship program and I already gave two session so the past two months have been somehow eventful, but still I’d say that it was my laziness and procrastination that prevented me from blogging this whole time.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Year Resolution</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/31/NewYearRes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Year Resolution" /><published>2021-12-31T04:45:13+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-31T04:45:13+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/31/NewYearRes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/31/NewYearRes.html"><![CDATA[<p>One benefit of having your birthday so close to new year eve is that you don’t have to make two resolutions. My plans for my 24th year of life and 2022 are the same thing. I have said before that this year was fairly good and I have learned new things, seen new places, and met some wonderful people. So today I’m sharing my goals for the year 2022!.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="things-to-learn">Things to learn</h3>

<p>I’ll never stop learning I want to learn new things all the time, but to be efficient here’s a list of things (other than computer vision) that I want to get good knowledge of. They are quite diverse and requires serious commitment but I’m hopeful (NEW YEAR SPIRIT!!feel the excitement, come on). Also having diverse set of skills can really help in todays highly competitive world you have to have some kind of rarefied set of skills that make you unique.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Web 3.0: if you’re not familiar I suggest you <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wHTcrmhskto">watch this</a>, but basically web 3.0 is a new decentralized internet were it’s not dominated by big “evil” tech companies like Facebook, Google, ..etc. It’s now widely known because of the boom in cryptocurrency and NFTs, metaverse  and decentralized apps.
A lot of people are skeptical about it (I’m too!!), but whereas you believe it is the next life changing tech or not is irrelevant. it’s becoming more and more important to understand at least the basics of block-chain technology and smart contacts it will change the world even if it fails because that just natural in technologies of this scale (it’s a billion dollar industry) there’s always winners and losers and lessons to learn so it is on the top of my list for the next year.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Cloud computing, edge computing and IOT: it’s the only natural next step for machine learning and AI. Edge computing allows for computation near the sources of data storage which allows for faster response time and save bandwidth.
 I’m already familiar with AWS (Amazon Web Services) and I remember a while ago I wanted to be solutions architect and finished the cloud practitioner course, but AWS is still unavailable in Sudan and I didn’t commit to it really, I was just intrigued.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Mathematics very often I find myself thinking about how much I need to understand some basic mathematical concepts, it’s shameful how bad my journey with mathematics was. even the purest of math that is not directly applicable to my fields of interests me now. I like to think of math as a language ! it really is if you think of it in certain way all I want is to be fluent in it.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>New language I’m not fully fluent in Spanish (hopefully I will be by the end of the year) but if I went to Spain it wouldn’t be too hard to live and interact with people and that exactly my goal I’m not doing it for a test or a scholarship I’m learning languages so I can communicate with people in their native language.
So give me your suggestions I considered Portuguese but it’s not that different I don’t want it to be too easy. I’m thinking maybe Italian, French, Russian, or German in that order. I know you might be wondering why new one instead of focusing on improving your Spanish? to which I answer why not both ;)
(NEW YEAR SPIRIT!! remember?).</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<hr />

<h4 id="some-notes-about-learning">Some Notes about learning</h4>

<p>having so much to learn can sometimes be as good as having nothing to learn, trying to learn more than you have time or abilities to can have some depressing results. I’m aware of this and I’ve been there before so I don’t have very high execepections for this let this be an expriment about how much I can learn about this four things in one year and on 2023/1/1 we will know the results (disappointing or suprising).</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="things-to-do">Things to do</h3>

<ul>
  <li>By the end of this year I want to look back and see that I was able to properly introduce new people to machine learning whereas through mentorship program, blog posts or any other way this will be a proof for me that I’m competent in this field.</li>
  <li>
    <p>I want to start my first job: hopefully kick starting my career in 2022.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I want to start working on some side projects: I have some ideas that never been truly considered for implementation. I will talk about them throughout the year in more details.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I want to contribute more consistently to tidytuesday to sharpen my data visualization and processing skills my aim is at least 10 times.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Journaling: I’ve tried this before I cann’t remember why I stopped actually, I’ll try to do it daily (let’s hope that  I manange to do for at least 200 days)
It’s easier to do understand oneself if we have a record of our feelings and highlights throughout the year (who knows maybe I’ll conduct some kind of analysis on the final data and make a model that is capable of predicting my feelings given who I meet and what season it is and things like that. (do you think facebook or google does not have a similar thing for you? think again!) ).</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="things-to-improve">Things to improve</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>typing speed: this year I wanted to reach at least 80-100, but I’m about 65 wpm now so let’s say 150 by the end of 2022? Also I want to learn Vim (text editor that totally frees you from using the mouse ) it has a steep learning curve but the payoff is huuuge.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Professional networking: I want to form more professional relationships with similar minded individuals I need to work on my social anxiety and start sharing my thoughts with people I’ll start with being more present in linkedin and going and participating in more events (I regeret not realizing this in my early collage years, or to be more honest beeing aware and choosing to neglect).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Spanish I’ve already mentioned this above.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Work out: What’s a new year resolution without workout goals right? This year (later half ) I managed to lose some weight and be slightly more active. I want to keep it up !</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="bounce">Bounce</h4>

<p>This for the inner child in me who still loves to draw and love drawings and art, but sadly I can’t do everything so I’ll be so glad if I’m able to find some time to give him want he wants: create cool art consistently :( .</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="a-lesson-learned">A Lesson learned</h3>

<p>one more self-improvement thing: I  want to be more direct and clear with people whenever I’m faced with uncomfortable or wierd situations.</p>

<p>one of the most important things that I learned this year(twice! both times the hard way) was that being unproblematic and understanding and just letting things slide can sometimes (actually most of the times) lead to only more complicated problems that you will eventually have to address, it will just be harder and more awkward that time. this was the case in my graduation project group, I’m glad and very relieved (even though it is very late ) that I confronted them and made points clear and didn’t just act weird about of the sudden. it’s not selfish or rude to call people out when they are overstepping or manipulating.</p>

<p>The truth will always make things easier, if you are afraid that the truth will ruin whatever kind of relationship you have with someone then you might have to reconsider and re-evaluate that relationship. Still however people won’t appreciate it if they feel that they are just under attack we need to communicate truth in a way that shows that it’s in everyone’s best interests (which it is!). I want to be able to also make it easier for people to tell me the truth.</p>

<p>Looking back at this year again this blog is my proudest achievement (beside being able to finish my graduation project despite all the problems) I was also surprised actaully that I’ve been somehow consistant(18 posts in 5 months !!) even though I wanted to quit twice!!.</p>

<p>There are two people in particular that I wanted to show my appreciation for their existence in my life Mayraf the best friend I ever had (simple as that), and Noon who despite that fact we have been friends for a short period of time, still influenced largly a lot of good things and decisions I made this year. this year was significantly better because of you two! Thank you.</p>

<p>Sadly I’ve also lost two good friends of mine, I wish our friendship didn’t end the way it it did, but that’s just life and I’m grateful for what we shared together. It’s for the best.</p>

<hr />

<p>In 2022</p>

<p>Don’t just lie, face.</p>

<p>Don’t just read, act.</p>

<p>Don’t just learn, teach. MJNFKLKFNBLKKLNFKLNBLNEMNWJPGIRJEFJO;eronno</p>

<p>Don’t just think, write.</p>

<p>Don’t just dream, fight, for everything.</p>

<p>With everything going on in Sudan now days to even have  plans or dreams might be foolish or very optimistic , but as they say it’s can sometimes be brave to allow yourself hope and “Fortes fortuna adiuvat” (“Fortune favours the brave”).</p>

<p>Happy New Year people! and see you in 2022.</p>

<p>you are stopid</p>]]></content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One benefit of having your birthday so close to new year eve is that you don’t have to make two resolutions. My plans for my 24th year of life and 2022 are the same thing. I have said before that this year was fairly good and I have learned new things, seen new places, and met some wonderful people. So today I’m sharing my goals for the year 2022!.]]></summary></entry></feed>