<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-04-22T21:52:17+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Raheem’s Blog</title><subtitle>My Opiniones on things and stuff</subtitle><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Path of The Rightous Man</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2022/04/22/I-lost-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Path of The Rightous Man" /><published>2022-04-22T06:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-22T06:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2022/04/22/I-lost-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2022/04/22/I-lost-it.html">&lt;p&gt;“Midway upon the journey of our life, I found myself within a forest dark, for the straightforward pathway had been lost.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;― Dante Alighieri, The Divine Comedy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while now since I’ve written my last post and a lot of things happened since then.
The idea of me stopping things like blogging and other activities I like for work or because I’m searching for a job have always haunted me but it seems like it’s to some extent unescapable.
I started feeling like Dante at the start of his journey through hell. The hardest thing after graduation is picking your own path but I found out that even when you know where you are going it’s not always enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by a short briefing of how horrible my new year resolution is going in the first quarter of 2022&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can barely pronounce the Russian alphabet (I wanted to challenge myself by learning a language from a different alphabet) regarding my language learning goals
Only 3 times I attempted to try tidytuesday and weren’t even public ones
I’m gaining weight again and almost neglecting all the computer vision tasks and plans
So in short it’s been hard to keep up with it and basiclly a major failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Career wise I was snubbed by Go. I felt bad, like really bad because it was a data related job but I also knew that I wasn’t really the best candidate and I didn’t perform well in the technical screening, so their decision was understandable but it still hurts.
Pushed by the desire to get my first job and get the illusion of financial independence I started another job it’s not as technically challenging or data centric as the one from Go but it still worth exploring two weeks in and I still haven’t fully made up my mind about it yet it has its pros and cons so no easy decision here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now feel lost, I was so naive thinking I wasn’t naive
Like I’ve always known that life is hard and that life after graduation is a lot harder than before it, but I somehow imagined it to be different. Let’s just say I thought it’s going to be hard in a different kind of way. Wishful thinking is of course one of the worst enemies you can have. It’s essentially thinking about things (or sometimes people) the way you wish they are not the way they really are. It can be a career path or it can even be your own abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if my current job will lead me to the career I want but then again do I even know what is? that and most importantly do I have what it takes to make it in that career
I think people, especially younger ones, tend to be passionate about their jobs now even though that’s not a bad thing but personally can view a job that way. I don’t think I just want to be one thing in life even though I know I kind of have to in today’s world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do I quit next week even though I had no problems so far or just wait and slowly drift away from the path I thought I’m going to walk? 
I should apply for scholarships and leave? then I’ll think about what will happens but that “then” will definitely come and all of this will be repeated but with the stakes being higher 
I don’t want to give up my dreams but sadly I know I might not afford to follow them sometimes you should just settle and realize that it can be luck sometimes that define your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;also a realization I had recently that if your life has been hard so far that means it’s probably going to get harder and not the oppiset and a lot of people tend to beileve which is like the Monte Carlo fallacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly don’t know what to do at this point of my life I feel there’s only bad and worse decisions here&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How you can sit there, calmly eating muffins when we are in
this horrible trouble, I can’t make out. You seem to me to be
perfectly heartless.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well, I can’t eat muffins in an agitated manner. The butter
would probably get on my cuffs. One should always eat muffins
quite calmly. It is the only way to eat them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I say it’s perfectly heartless you are eating muffins at all, under
the circumstances.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oscar Wilde, The Importance of Being Earnest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this quote a lot because sometimes all we need is little calmness to make the right decision or at least or lack of calmness and mindfulness leads to even worse decisions so for now I’m just going to try to “eat my muffins” without letting the butter get on my cuffs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by the way (if you haven’t guess already ) The title of this post comes from pulp fiction one of my all time favorite movies this quote said by jules twice in the movie but when he was explaining  what this made up verse meant in the restaurant scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ezekiel 25:17. “The path of the righteous man is beset on all sides by the inequities of the selfish and the tyranny of evil men. Blessed is he who, in the name of charity and good will, shepherds the weak through the valley of the darkness. For he is truly his brother’s keeper and the finder of lost children. And I will strike down upon thee with great vengeance and furious anger those who attempt to poison and destroy my brothers. And you will know I am the Lord when I lay my vengeance upon you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…it could be you’re the righteous man and I’m the shepherd and it’s the world that’s evil and selfish. I’d like that. But that shit ain’t the truth. The truth is you’re the weak. And I’m the tyranny of evil men. But I’m tryin, Ringo. I’m tryin’ real hard to be the shepherd.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been telling this to myself now that instead of looking at the world as an evil or selfish place it was me who is weak and needs to be stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of my happiest moments of the past few months. I never thought I would miss doing this and the fact that this blog will be 1 year old  in less than 3 months is actually crazy and makes me panic thinking about how fast time is moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I make another post(s) soon and it won’t take me 3 months to do so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">“Midway upon the journey of our life, I found myself within a forest dark, for the straightforward pathway had been lost.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Abolishing The Educational System</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2022/02/22/Abolishing-the-education-system.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Abolishing The Educational System" /><published>2022-02-22T06:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2022-02-22T06:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2022/02/22/Abolishing-the-education-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2022/02/22/Abolishing-the-education-system.html">&lt;p&gt;Long time no see I kind of missed my own blog isn’t that sad, but finally I finished college (hopefully that will be official next week) and I was busy with exams, graduation project and another project also I was a part of a mentorship program and I already gave two session so the past two months have been somehow eventful, but still I’d say that it was my laziness and procrastination that prevented me from blogging this whole time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Place a wager on your greed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wager on your pride&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why try to beat them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a million tried?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember reading this somewhere on George Hotz blog. Since then it has become one of my favorite quotes (I think it’s from a song or something) whenever I’m thinking of doing something that’s basically too much or sounds nuts like “abolishing the education system”. I know I’m not the first to think of this or try to do it but someone has to beat it even if a million tried (and failed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not an anarchist. I’m not talking about the whole education system at once or preventing people from going to schools, but also I don’t like the fact that this is the de facto of education and people sort of just agreed upon it. It is worthwhile to think about what people consider the normal or the standard way of doing things. Most of the great inventions were just a product of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help you trace back the things that led me to think of this is that at the end of college I just realized how much time and effort can be saved both in the long and the short run simply by adopting smarter methods for education. I’m not exaggerating if I said I’ve learned more than 90% of my courses from YouTube and other websites  and honestly I can see why it’s not possible for someone to get to 100% if given the right guidance which is basically the job of your professors and teachers but that is not happening. Besides, I really hated my college and this is my way of directing these negative feelings towards a good cause.
As a start I genuinely want to fully replace my faculty (fmsi) with an online platform that contains the information, knowledge, resources and method of evaluation for an equivalent of a bachelor degree in math computer science and statistics 
I think these fields are the best start to a much larger change that will make education more efficient, flexible and accessible for all.Computer science courses by nature are the easiest to be completely made online. There’s a plethora of resources already available however for math and statistics that might be harder.
This doesn’t have to be super complex or even useful from the start I won’t let my desire for perfection to hold me from getting started this time similar to this blog it will grow and I’ll try to create the right environment for it to grow&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thats-not-new-or-original&quot;&gt;That’s not new or original&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originality is overrated 
I think no matter how old an idea is you can still create a lot of new value by improving it and building upon it, doing it better or even by just simply looking at it from a different perspective
Google wasn’t the first search engine 
Facebook wasn’t the first social media 
“Go” was the last ride sharing app to enter the Sudanese market yet all of this examples are the dominant names in their respective fields 
My point is even though there’s a lot of previous efforts to democratize education and make it more available, affordable and overall effective and efficient which is great, I guess there’s still a room for improvement. In this day and age it might seem like everything that can be done has already been done but there’s a simple rule I following regarding creating content and related things which is if you searched for something and didn’t find it online then there’s a chance to create it and benefit from it because there’s a lot of people similar to you that would appreciate it and be excited by it and this is one of the thing that will help me in this project which is the power of the people. I believe that most of the  people who study computer science have learned so much from free online sources and because of that they have the desire to help others the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-can-you-help-me&quot;&gt;How can you help me?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally everyone can help in this  no matter what is your skill and skill level 
I will soon get into more detail, but first I need to know what people think of this, so for now you can spread the word and tell your friends about this and tell me what you think.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">Long time no see I kind of missed my own blog isn’t that sad, but finally I finished college (hopefully that will be official next week) and I was busy with exams, graduation project and another project also I was a part of a mentorship program and I already gave two session so the past two months have been somehow eventful, but still I’d say that it was my laziness and procrastination that prevented me from blogging this whole time.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Year Resolution</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/31/NewYearRes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Year Resolution" /><published>2021-12-31T06:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-12-31T06:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/31/NewYearRes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/31/NewYearRes.html">&lt;p&gt;One benefit of having your birthday so close to new year eve is that you don’t have to make two resolutions. My plans for my 24th year of life and 2022 are the same thing. I have said before that this year was fairly good and I have learned new things, seen new places, and met some wonderful people. So today I’m sharing my goals for the year 2022!.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-to-learn&quot;&gt;Things to learn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll never stop learning I want to learn new things all the time, but to be efficient here’s a list of things (other than computer vision) that I want to get good knowledge of. They are quite diverse and requires serious commitment but I’m hopeful (NEW YEAR SPIRIT!!feel the excitement, come on). Also having diverse set of skills can really help in todays highly competitive world you have to have some kind of rarefied set of skills that make you unique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Web 3.0: if you’re not familiar I suggest you &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wHTcrmhskto&quot;&gt;watch this&lt;/a&gt;, but basically web 3.0 is a new decentralized internet were it’s not dominated by big “evil” tech companies like Facebook, Google, ..etc. It’s now widely known because of the boom in cryptocurrency and NFTs, metaverse  and decentralized apps.
A lot of people are skeptical about it (I’m too!!), but whereas you believe it is the next life changing tech or not is irrelevant. it’s becoming more and more important to understand at least the basics of block-chain technology and smart contacts it will change the world even if it fails because that just natural in technologies of this scale (it’s a billion dollar industry) there’s always winners and losers and lessons to learn so it is on the top of my list for the next year.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloud computing, edge computing and IOT: it’s the only natural next step for machine learning and AI. Edge computing allows for computation near the sources of data storage which allows for faster response time and save bandwidth.
 I’m already familiar with AWS (Amazon Web Services) and I remember a while ago I wanted to be solutions architect and finished the cloud practitioner course, but AWS is still unavailable in Sudan and I didn’t commit to it really, I was just intrigued.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mathematics very often I find myself thinking about how much I need to understand some basic mathematical concepts, it’s shameful how bad my journey with mathematics was. even the purest of math that is not directly applicable to my fields of interests me now. I like to think of math as a language ! it really is if you think of it in certain way all I want is to be fluent in it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;New language I’m not fully fluent in Spanish (hopefully I will be by the end of the year) but if I went to Spain it wouldn’t be too hard to live and interact with people and that exactly my goal I’m not doing it for a test or a scholarship I’m learning languages so I can communicate with people in their native language.
So give me your suggestions I considered Portuguese but it’s not that different I don’t want it to be too easy. I’m thinking maybe Italian, French, Russian, or German in that order. I know you might be wondering why new one instead of focusing on improving your Spanish? to which I answer why not both ;)
(NEW YEAR SPIRIT!! remember?).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;some-notes-about-learning&quot;&gt;Some Notes about learning&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;having so much to learn can sometimes be as good as having nothing to learn, trying to learn more than you have time or abilities to can have some depressing results. I’m aware of this and I’ve been there before so I don’t have very high execepections for this let this be an expriment about how much I can learn about this four things in one year and on 2023/1/1 we will know the results (disappointing or suprising).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-to-do&quot;&gt;Things to do&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By the end of this year I want to look back and see that I was able to properly introduce new people to machine learning whereas through mentorship program, blog posts or any other way this will be a proof for me that I’m competent in this field.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to start my first job: hopefully kick starting my career in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to start working on some side projects: I have some ideas that never been truly considered for implementation. I will talk about them throughout the year in more details.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to contribute more consistently to tidytuesday to sharpen my data visualization and processing skills my aim is at least 10 times.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Journaling: I’ve tried this before I cann’t remember why I stopped actually, I’ll try to do it daily (let’s hope that  I manange to do for at least 200 days)
It’s easier to do understand oneself if we have a record of our feelings and highlights throughout the year (who knows maybe I’ll conduct some kind of analysis on the final data and make a model that is capable of predicting my feelings given who I meet and what season it is and things like that. (do you think facebook or google does not have a similar thing for you? think again!) ).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-to-improve&quot;&gt;Things to improve&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;typing speed: this year I wanted to reach at least 80-100, but I’m about 65 wpm now so let’s say 150 by the end of 2022? Also I want to learn Vim (text editor that totally frees you from using the mouse ) it has a steep learning curve but the payoff is huuuge.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Professional networking: I want to form more professional relationships with similar minded individuals I need to work on my social anxiety and start sharing my thoughts with people I’ll start with being more present in linkedin and going and participating in more events (I regeret not realizing this in my early collage years, or to be more honest beeing aware and choosing to neglect).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spanish I’ve already mentioned this above.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Work out: What’s a new year resolution without workout goals right? This year (later half ) I managed to lose some weight and be slightly more active. I want to keep it up !&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bounce&quot;&gt;Bounce&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This for the inner child in me who still loves to draw and love drawings and art, but sadly I can’t do everything so I’ll be so glad if I’m able to find some time to give him want he wants: create cool art consistently :( .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-lesson-learned&quot;&gt;A Lesson learned&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;one more self-improvement thing: I  want to be more direct and clear with people whenever I’m faced with uncomfortable or wierd situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;one of the most important things that I learned this year(twice! both times the hard way) was that being unproblematic and understanding and just letting things slide can sometimes (actually most of the times) lead to only more complicated problems that you will eventually have to address, it will just be harder and more awkward that time. this was the case in my graduation project group, I’m glad and very relieved (even though it is very late ) that I confronted them and made points clear and didn’t just act weird about of the sudden. it’s not selfish or rude to call people out when they are overstepping or manipulating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth will always make things easier, if you are afraid that the truth will ruin whatever kind of relationship you have with someone then you might have to reconsider and re-evaluate that relationship. Still however people won’t appreciate it if they feel that they are just under attack we need to communicate truth in a way that shows that it’s in everyone’s best interests (which it is!). I want to be able to also make it easier for people to tell me the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at this year again this blog is my proudest achievement (beside being able to finish my graduation project despite all the problems) I was also surprised actaully that I’ve been somehow consistant(18 posts in 5 months !!) even though I wanted to quit twice!!.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two people in particular that I wanted to show my appreciation for their existence in my life Mayraf the best friend I ever had (simple as that), and Noon who despite that fact we have been friends for a short period of time, still influenced largly a lot of good things and decisions I made this year. this year was significantly better because of you two! Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly I’ve also lost two good friends of mine, I wish our friendship didn’t end the way it it did, but that’s just life and I’m grateful for what we shared together. It’s for the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2022&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t just lie, face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t just read, act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t just learn, teach. MJNFKLKFNBLKKLNFKLNBLNEMNWJPGIRJEFJO;eronno&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t just think, write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t just dream, fight, for everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With everything going on in Sudan now days to even have  plans or dreams might be foolish or very optimistic , but as they say it’s can sometimes be brave to allow yourself hope and “Fortes fortuna adiuvat” (“Fortune favours the brave”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year people! and see you in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you are stopid&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">One benefit of having your birthday so close to new year eve is that you don’t have to make two resolutions. My plans for my 24th year of life and 2022 are the same thing. I have said before that this year was fairly good and I have learned new things, seen new places, and met some wonderful people. So today I’m sharing my goals for the year 2022!.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intelligence</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/20/Intelligence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intelligence" /><published>2021-12-20T06:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-12-20T06:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/20/Intelligence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/20/Intelligence.html">&lt;p&gt;“Looked at in one way, everyone knows what
intelligence is; looked at in another way, no
one does.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence is currently one of the fastest growing fields in the world, also most of the research in computer science is dedicated to it, almost half of all the research in computer science is now about A.I and related fields. But before we make it artificial we need to first define, understand, and measure it. This post is inspired by a paper I recently read, made in 2019 by francois chollet, francois is one of the pioneers in the field and one of the people that I highly look up to and admire because of his amazing way of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper describes intelligence as “skill-acquisition efficiency” opposed to the common way that is used which is by comparing the results between the A.I performance and human performance in a specific task. To consider an agent intelligenet it must have the ability to acquire new skills and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between human and A.I now days is that A.I can get good at some tasks sometimes even better than human (Alphazero for example is a chess playing A.I that Practically unbeatable! take a minute and think about this!  no human being will ever beat A.I in chess! similarly AlphaGo is another one for the game of Go and many more were made for atari games and different games) but even then, human still way more intelligent because they can &lt;em&gt;adapt&lt;/em&gt; to any changes of the rules or the environment. on the other hand A.I needs relatively long time and human involvement and supervision to adjust to the smallest changes.(consider changing the rules of chess the way the knight moves or the queen moves I will argue that an average chess player will beat Alphazero then)  to achieve real A.I this should not be the case A.I agents should be equipped to lean how to learn novel tasks that they never seen before!.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;mayraf (my best friend) is a very good chess player he is actually the best chess player I have ever known in my life, he is also better at chess than any of my friends at any of their things(hobbies, games, etc…), but still mayraf was not born knowing chess nor we can say that god made him only to play chess, but we can safely assume that he is an intelligent person, because we implicitly know that he had to use his general intelligence to acquire this specific skill over his lifetime, which reflects his general ability to acquire many other possible skills in the same way.  The
same assumption does not apply to a non-human system that does not arrive at competence
the way humans do. We need A.I agents to be able to repurpose their abilities to learn new skills the same way mayraf can learn other games using the same abilities he used for learning chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Even though such machines might do some
things as well as we do them, or perhaps even
better, they would inevitably fail in others,
which would reveal they were acting not
through understanding, but only from the
disposition of their organs.” - Rene Descartes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-want-ai-to-generalize&quot;&gt;We want A.I to generalize&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we now have a goal to make A.I generalize, to  perform well even in novel situations, but even this needs more clarification we can divided generalization to two types
system-centeric generalization which means situation that are new to the A.I agent, and developer-aware generalization which means to perform well even in situations that are new to the A.I’s developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;we-can-also-qualitatively-define-degrees-of-generalization-to&quot;&gt;we can also qualitatively define degrees of generalization to&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Absence of generalization:&lt;/strong&gt;this is generalization in the sense of mathematical proofs we can not say a program generalize if it’s just producing a proven mathematical relationship Likewise, a sorting algorithm that is proven to be correct cannot be said to “generalize” to all lists of
integers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local generalization, or “robustness”:&lt;/strong&gt; This is the ability of a system to handle new
points from a known distribution for a single task or a well-scoped set of known tasks,
given a sufficiently dense sampling of examples from the distribution (e.g. tolerance
to anticipated perturbations within a fixed context). For instance, an image classifier
that can distinguish previously unseen 150x150 RGB images containing cats from
those containing dogs, after being trained on many such labeled images, can be said
to perform local generalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Broad generalization, or “flexibility”:&lt;/strong&gt; This is the ability of a system to handle a
broad category of tasks and environments without further human intervention. For instance, a L5 self-driving vehicle, or a domestic robot capable
of passing Wozniak’s coffee cup test (entering a random kitchen and making a cup of
coffee) could be said to display broad generalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extreme generalization:&lt;/strong&gt; This describes open-ended systems with the ability to handle entirely new tasks that only share abstract commonalities with previously encountered situations, applicable to any task and domain within a wide scope. This could
be characterized as “adaptation to unknown unknowns across an unknown range of
tasks and domains”. Biological forms of intelligence (humans and possibly other intelligent species) are the only example of such a system at this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;do-we-care-if-a-plane-eats-fish-&quot;&gt;Do we care if a plane eats fish ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can we make human level generalization? key step is to deeper understand how our mind work, how it can turn experience into behavior, knowledge and skills.
I’ve came across this blog post by george hotz I really like this idea (not that of a fish eating planes of course!). He was saying that to achieve this performance we need to look differently at how we preserve our brains
“There’s two papers I love that illustrate what understanding a system really means. Can a biologist fix a radio? (2002) and Could a Neuroscientist Understand a Microprocessor? (2017). To me, they illustrate that the current tools of biology and sub-fields are unequipped to handle understanding life. We will know we understand life once we can build life. We will know we understand a brain once we can build a brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s going to end up looking like birds and planes. Planes fly in a much more “rigid” way, and they are much simpler than birds. But for our purposes, planes are more useful, and nobody would deny that they are “flying machines”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody will deny that our artificial life are “thinking machines.” Nobody will care if the machine can “love” in the same way nobody cares if a plane eats fish. We will care if we’ve built something that can do everything useful that a human can do.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more post left in this year! I think this is actually the 16th post so far, I really did came a long way in these past 5 months all of this wouldn’t have been possible if it wasn’t for your support and encouragement so thanks again. I’m also considering sharing this blog with larger audience (hopefully soon) 
Next post would be a year recap and what I’m looking forward to in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">“Looked at in one way, everyone knows what intelligence is; looked at in another way, no one does.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Time</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/13/Time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Time" /><published>2021-12-13T06:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-12-13T06:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/13/Time</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/13/Time.html">&lt;p&gt;Time is without any doubt our most valuable asset in this life. No matter what else you have it’s nothing if you don’t have time to enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is a weird thing too ! I mean people just decided what an hour is and what a day is and we sort of justed agreed to it.
For example there’s a lot of calendars on earth. Here’s a random fact(that I find very interesting ) about the names of the months in the most used calendar &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.almanac.com/content/how-did-months-get-their-names&quot;&gt;Gregorian calendar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter how you think of it or calculate it, there’s some facts about it: it’s limited, finite, and most certainly there is no enough of it. (Given the current technology at least maybe that can change in the future).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is kind of interesting (time for some philosophy): would you like immortality? I mean obviously yes, but when you think about it for a while if we are immortals then there will be no urgency to anything no eagerness, if I don’t meet you today I’ll meet you next month or maybe in the next 700 years, if I don’t do it now I’ll just do it later or next year or next century.
Nothing will mean anything!, it will be literally torture!.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will accept immortality under one condition maybe, if I’m not aware of it. I want to learn everything I want to try everything the only way to do that I think is to be immortal without any awareness of it. but hey enough of the philosophy, you know what they say about philosophers? they are just people who discovered weed way too old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studying in a university as unstable as university of Khartoum I have experienced how having plenty of free time can be counterproductive, whenever it’s closed I have this urge to learn new skills or improve the ones I have, But soon as I realize that I have more time and no deadlines,  every today  =becomes tomorrow and every tomorrow becomes next week until couple months down the road I wish I started few months earlier. Then you start self loathing and being depressed about it leading you to waste even more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I (similar to a lot of people) got one thing about productivity wrong. I thought I have to be in my best physical and mental state to be productive, but the truth is -at least for me- is that productivity what’s really gives me good feelings it’s hard to get started when you are not motivated but once I actually set down and start working on something I end up being much happier and satisfied at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is becoming hard place to be  productive, with social media reducing our attention span to less than that of a golden fish, so stimulating that it’s actually boring, drawing your attention to things you don’t actually care about stealing the most valuable hours of your day.
I hate social media so much I hope one day I’ll be able to live without it, that seems impossible at this point which is kind of sad so maybe I’ll just try to focus on the positive sides of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of social media and attention I highly recommend that you read a book  called deep work by  This book showed me a lot of important things about the topic of this post I wont go over any details here just read it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attack-the-day&quot;&gt;Attack the day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever watched “dead poets society”? it’s a good movies, not one of my favorites but still, There’s a quote from this movies which is in Latin that says “carpie diem!” it translates to “seize the day!” It’s important to attack your day, start early and get to work think of it this way it’s like play &lt;strong&gt;x  o&lt;/strong&gt; with the day If you made the first move you chances of winning are actually very high, it will be in your hands to decide if you want to win or lose.
I have experienced this many times some days I wake up open my laptop and just pick some book or write some code or study for some times these days almost always feel longer than others Which is another thing I was wrong about, being productive (I just realized that I have not give any definition to productivity yet, let’s just say it’s how much each day contributes to your overall goals and duties in life. And this “much” is actually hard to measure it does not have to be just the number of hours) gives you more time to do other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain: I’m always paranoid about not being productive but at the same time a quite lazy person who procrastinate a lot so the result is more time goes to self blame. On the other hand when I manage somehow to win the first round of the day I ended more motivated to do more things like hobbies and stuff without feeling like I have other things to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;building-a-habit&quot;&gt;Building a habit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constructing the perfect loop is nearly impossible in this country so maintaining a long time plan will almost certainly fail that’s why you should create backup plans all the time for all scenarios
No electricity or no internet or any other reason can easily ruin your plans.
I’m thinking of making some routine for my weeks from now on
I don’t mean this will be what I’m doing the whole day, but you can think of it as the “theme” of the day I’m able to function with 6 hours of sleep everyday (and almost no social life lol ) so I still have a plenty of time to do other important things I hope to integrate this in my working life after graduation or at least a lighter variation of it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Monday blog&lt;/em&gt; day I write the and publish a new post. I rarely write a whole post in one sitting or one day but I’ll try to stitch things together and search for good topics and things like that, I’m dedicating more time so I can deliver you better content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TidyTuesday&lt;/em&gt; is already a thing so that will be the day for data analysis visualization and similar stuff&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wednesday web day&lt;/em&gt; I hate the fact that I learn so much about web development and I never used that knowledge and skills so I’m planning on re-sharping them doing small scale side projects and maybe I’ll come up with the next billion dollar idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Theory Thursday&lt;/em&gt; since I’m committed to computer vision I need to have solid theoretical  foundation on a lot of complicated topics so this day I go back old school pen and paper stuff and learn from the principles. Also important and interesting papers are read on this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Free-day Friday&lt;/em&gt; it’s the day I get to be lazy I can do whatever I want. I have recently made commitment to one of my friends to monitor him in machine learning so maybe things like that get sorted here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday is for non academic reading and general knowledge and language learning and practicing.(I bet you are disappointed that I didn’t give it any name)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday backup day  in case I wasn’t able to fulfill this tasks. I wanted it to be at the beginning  of the week because I believe I’ll be more motivated at that time to finish any unresolved stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m 2 weeks away from being 24 years old I can’t say this is how I imagined my life would be at this age, that is very sad actually, plus when start to lose your hair it’s like having a count down over your head everyday you slowly and literally fading away one hair at a time. 30s are nearer and they are scary and many agrees that 40s are the fastest decade of your life so maybe I don’t have as much time as I think (if I’m able to stay alive till that time). I know, I know this sounds very melodramatic but it’s depression season again and I think I get to make some drama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on other bright sides this year wasn’t actually very bad would’ve been near perfect if I had graduated but &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;it is what it is&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. My biggest achievements are probably: Starting this blog, finding a career path that I’m very interested in,  I think I improved my Spanish language skills, I’ve made a very cool new friend, but most importantly I think I no longer hate myself! and I’m starting to actually belief in my abilities. Let’s hope that I see the benefits of that soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">Time is without any doubt our most valuable asset in this life. No matter what else you have it’s nothing if you don’t have time to enjoy it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I think I found it !</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/04/found-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I think I found it !" /><published>2021-12-04T09:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-12-04T09:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/04/found-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/04/found-it.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is actually an old post that I wrote a while ago but I didn’t publish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was setting frustrated going through 52  open tabs on my browser looking for some help for my graduation project “maybe you bit off more than you can chew huh” I thought to myself, it seemed to me that this project is never going to be finished. but in that moment of despair it came to me, as I was going through the resources tutorials, lectures, and code notebooks I’ve realized how much I’m fascinated by the idea of computer vision. This made things little bit less painful for me because this is something I really want to be good at and since I’m having troubles that meant at least I’m learning something new. It’s weird that it wasn’t until final weeks that I realized I picked up something might actually be my career&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer vision -as the name implies- is a computer science discipline that deals with how computers can gain high-level understanding from digital images or videos or any other visual input. People think it’s subfield of A.I, but  Computer Vison had been around for years before the explotion of AI  and many methods were developed solve its problems without AI. It just happens that since the introduction of Deep learning and CNN “convolutional neural networks” they’ve been outperforming all the other method. Now with the availability of data and computation power to process it, the field is tackling more and more interesting problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of computers being able to identify,classify and segment objects form images or videos which fundamentally makes them “see” just like us is actually both scary and amazing. We are yet to achieve that, Tesla (which is considered a poineer in the field) is yet to deliver a full automated self-driving cars dispite claims from elon musk. Self-driving cars are cool but they are not the only application to Computer Vison, diseases detection (as in my graduation project), object character recognition (OCR), disasters early warning systems (This was actully my first idea for my graduation project) are some highlights of this field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what&quot;&gt;So what?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so now you probably thinking: “well,  that’s cool, but what’s your plan?”. “Are this application implementable here in Sudan?”. “Is this a reasonable career choice ?”. To be honest I haven’t made a detailed plan yet but I’m working on it, but here is the big ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;get-a-mentor&quot;&gt;get a mentor&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;mentors are so important I wish I knew this earlier they can help you save so much time and effort and learn from their experience. About a year ago I was a part of a machine learning mentorship program and I had an exceptional mentor who had incredible experience in Computer vison, but unfortunately we had to stop the mentorship program about two weeks in. I haven’t made contact with him since, which is a shame really because I think I should have benifited more from him, however, I’m currently searching for someone with experinece in computer vision (tell me if you know someone ).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;literature-review&quot;&gt;literature review&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I want to be great at computer vision there’s a lot of research papers that I should go through. I’ll have to study hard (almost) daily just to keep up. I’m starting with the basics. I’m making a list of the essential papers to read in the fieald of computer vison including papers on (CNN archetictrues, transformers, GANs, etc). Also computer Vison in closely related to robotic and reinforcement learning especially in the context of self-driving cars so I have to keep up with that too.
 I have also started looking at comma.ai’s openpiolt code (for these of you who don’t know comma.ai is a company that is competing with telsa think of it this way: if tesla was apple for self-driving cars then comma is Android  because is it is open sourced. Maybe I’ll make a post comparing the two in details ) at first it seemed it very complicated, but thanks to thier own blog I was able to get the jest of it.
 I’m trying to create my own master dgree curiclumm there’s some courses (all of which are freely availble in youtube ) three from univercity
of tuebingen  and other from NYU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;practice-makes-perfect&quot;&gt;practice makes perfect&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along side the theoritical part there must also be practical work to cement this ideas. Kaggle is all you can ask for  beginner to advanced the amount of knowledge you can get from is absolutely ridiculous and with their free GPUs and TPUs you can actually work with very complex and interesting data without worrying about hardware/software issues.
I’m aware of the big difference between doing data science and machine learning in kaggle vs real life. there is a very important steps in the whole process that kaggle makes invisable for you, Now while being aware of this defferences is important it’s also important to remember that in real life you work in teams in you probably wont find yourself worrying about everything on a real job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;let-the-people-see&quot;&gt;let the people see&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important steps. talking is easy, show your results. I’m learn how to deploy models and embed them on application on different platforms. My web develompent skills will come handy here, I’m thinking of adding a projects page on this blog where I share my work with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;connect-with-similar-minded-people&quot;&gt;connect with similar minded people&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;networking is probabaly the hardest thing on this list. Being an introvert in a world where your network and connection can get further than your talent or skills can ever do, it sometimes depressing, but I will have to learn to play by the rules, maybe the reason I hate working with other people is that I never did I might actually like it who knows,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-problem-in-context-of-sudan&quot;&gt;The problem in context of Sudan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there’s a big resistance to technology in general and rightfully so. If you ever used bankak which is a digital banking app for one of Sudan largest banks (I think it has the most clients) but it is so full of bugs, laggy and lacking the essence of digital banking which is spontaneousness. That’s for an arguably very simple and common use case so you could imagine the reaction to computer vision application (it is easier to convince some one that an application can calculate your trancsactions, but to tell them it can diagnose your medical images huh no way, and that of course given that we have a sophisticated enough AI to really diagnose )
It’s not the all bankak fault though, the overall infrastructure of telecommunications in this country is questionable not to mention things like syber securit. ..etc.But still it’s not completely hopeless yet (let’s hope I’m not wrong)
How can we re-gain Sudanese people trust in technology that’s an idea for another post for another time.
Also people always seem to undermine the influnce AI in general can have on sudanese people life because they have a very rigid and specific ideas of how in can be used. It doesn’t have to be complex to be useful technology is measured by the value it creates in people’s life not by how sophisticated it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;what about you? what do you think about Computer Vision and do you have an idea about an application that utilize it ? what do you want your computer to see?.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">Note</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Optimism</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/04/optimism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Optimism" /><published>2021-12-04T08:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-12-04T08:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/04/optimism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/04/optimism.html">&lt;h3&gt; &quot;Pessimists sounds smart but optimists make money&quot;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m largely described as pessimistic person, I can always come up with scenarios where things can go wrong or horribly, and the problem is most of the times they (the scenarios) can be very convincing and logical, I’ve managed to discourage my self and others times and times again claiming to be realistic and wise. That’s why I started this post with that quote not exactly money but anything of value really, most of the times it can seem to be unwise or unrealistic to take risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was still a kid I thought about changing the world, thought of it as inevitable thing that one day I’ll be someone great but as life went by year after year I started acknowledging that as unattainable goal slowly I’ve become the opposite of that child “nothing I’ll ever do will ever be of any value. why even bother? success in largely defined by luck” this practically been my motto for the past few years. This probably why I never commited to any hobby I like to draw be I’ve always saw my drawings as trash and convinced myself that I do not have the talent&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I want to recover some of that child-like optimism my goal is to work at tesla or comma.ai (both are the leading companies in creating self-drive cars) this is the closest thing I have for a life goal but I don’t want to work there just because its name or salary but to contribute significantly to one of the most fascinating problems mankind has attempted to solve 
(More on this on a separate post)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Is it hard? Yes very&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Is there's a high competition from thousands of highly motivated and dedicated people from all around the world who has better education and overall living conditions? Also yes&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Does it require a lot of hard work and sacrifices without any guarantees of any kind success ? Yes 
Am I going to pursue it despite being aware of all of this ? Yes&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\img\optim.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;unchanged&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s be honest here for a second mathematically and statistically my chances doesn’t look great and you reading this right now might think it’s very far fetched and even laughable and I’ll only end up regretting wasting my time trying to do it, but it’s okay. It’s important to let ourselves be vulnerable to getting disappointed and getting hurt because at the end it’s not about protecting ourselves from getting hurt it’s about not minding it for a greater cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only as career advice it’s the same in friendship and  love without risking being uncomfortable and vulnerable we can’t maintain healthy relationships don’t give in to your psychological defense mechanisms.
I think it’s good to use workout analogy you don’t gain muscle unless you tear your muscles first by doing hard exercises that are beyond your current abilities the recovery of the tore muscles is what makes you gain muscles. Similarly you need to do the same to your mentality the less you’re mentally challenged the weaker you get and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worst case scenario I will learn a lot of things about me and about different things in life and gain a lot of technical skills a long the journey so really it’s not only about the destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important for me to tell me your opinion on this and whether you believe I can do it or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">&quot;Pessimists sounds smart but optimists make money&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I’m Back!</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/04/Im-back.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I’m Back!" /><published>2021-12-04T07:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-12-04T07:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/04/Im-back</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/12/04/Im-back.html">&lt;p&gt;Let just say that October is now my least favorite month of the year, it started awfully and somehow managed to finish even worse. By 20th October I was at one of the most stressful periods I had in a while academically, socially, financially and most importantly mentally.  The combination of this factors lead me to be in mental state I thought I would never be in  again (state where you do not want to do things rationally and just want to make things go away and misdirecting your anger at the wrong things and people ), but still all of this was somehow bearable because I’m few weeks away from graduating so that was one thing helping me, but When the coup happened few days later the feelings of hopelessness and despair magnified. I was so shocked and I actually laughed for how serreal was the situation. Nothing made sense to me “this can’t be really happening”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly (and thankfully) I’m all good now I think coming back is the prove. I was reminded how little control I have over the course my life , well maybe ‘little’ is not the right word to use, but the point is you should focus only on what is within your ability to change. when will you graduate? Definitely not one of them. I stopped caring to the point I no longer care when or even if I ever do. I’m not a nihilist who thinks nothing means anything even though I admit to think like that sometimes. These kind of feelings stems from not being able to achieve what I believe I’m more than capable of achieving, but then again this projections you have are fundamentally unfair because of your unawareness of your control boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;also I want to say that living without internet was one of the best things that happened to me in 2021. thanks to it I finally managed to started reading the books in my library.
one book that I would like to recommed that you read is “deep work” by Cal Newport I didn’t finish it but really like most of what I found in it.
another thing that I was able to do because of the free time I had in the absence of the internet is to listin more to podcast mainly spanish teaching ones and lex fridman podcast which is in my opinion the best of all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to make this long one, so long story short I’m back and I’m better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.s special thanks to “git reset -Hard 87d2f41f” couldn’t have done it without you (literally hahaha).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">Let just say that October is now my least favorite month of the year, it started awfully and somehow managed to finish even worse. By 20th October I was at one of the most stressful periods I had in a while academically, socially, financially and most importantly mentally. The combination of this factors lead me to be in mental state I thought I would never be in again (state where you do not want to do things rationally and just want to make things go away and misdirecting your anger at the wrong things and people ), but still all of this was somehow bearable because I’m few weeks away from graduating so that was one thing helping me, but When the coup happened few days later the feelings of hopelessness and despair magnified. I was so shocked and I actually laughed for how serreal was the situation. Nothing made sense to me “this can’t be really happening”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happiness</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/10/16/Happiness.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happiness" /><published>2021-10-16T07:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-16T07:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/10/16/Happiness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/10/16/Happiness.html">&lt;p&gt;Happiness is for sure one of the hardest topics to talk about, and I know that I said I’ll keep things short and simple, but I actually started this post a few weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What brought up this topic was when I came across this quote from Albert Einstein:(Written in old age)”I have never belonged wholeheartedly to a country, a state, nor to a circle of friends, nor even to my own family. When I was still a rather precocious young man, I already realized most vividly the futility of the hopes and aspirations that most men pursue throughout their lives. Well-being and happiness never appeared to me as an absolute aim. I am even inclined to compare such moral aims to the ambitions of a pig.”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This somehow relatable, even though the later part is kind of harsh I mean “inclined to compare such morals to the ambitions of a pig” I wouldn’t go that far, but I’m not here to argue with Mr. Einstein (who would want to ?). I remember while ago on Twitter there was this debate on whereas “money can’t buy happiness” is a complete nonsense and that materialistic pleasure can bring you true happiness or at least comfort and peace of mind. First and quickly I just want to say that I really wish people stopped arguing on Twitter and stopped taking it seriously I rarely ever found someone that changed his mind about something based on strangers opinions on Twitter in one word: it’s pointless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now back to the Topic. The  way I think of money is that it’s a tool to mainly buy time, for example I won’t work at a job that pays more but takes away so much of my non-work time because that would basically be meaningless. I have to make time for family time for hobbies I can’t be completely defined by the job I do no matter how I’m passionate about it. What’s interesting about our lives is that we can’t always choose the obvious simple solutions. Most of the time you have to calculate a lot of factors, and I think that this where the idea of not having to worry about money can be viewed as proxy for happiness. Now that you have free time and money what do you do? Our brains have this ability to normalize (I also hate Twitter for ruining words, this word for example I couldn’t write it without feeling stupid) any state we are in good or bad. You would crave something for so long and once you get it’s now nothing and the same when you lose something very precious. This essential to make life bearable. I think whereas you have money or not influence largely your views on if it canbring true happiness and fulfillment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money can give you comfort and time with yourself but the more time you’ll have with yourself the more you’ll look for deeper meaning to your life.
I’m currently broke and I know money can solve many of the problems I have, but in the end I can’t scape me, I know that there’s things that no amount of money can change or fix. It can only distract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happiness is an indicator that you are living your life in alignment with your own goals and beliefs it can sometimes be in midst of much suffering and physical discomfort (athletes for examples) we are truly happy and on the contrary well-off people might find themselves in valley of despair and life becomes unbearable for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy when I’m writing this posts. I’m also happy to know that some people read them and find them useful or insightful or interesting. For a few minutes every now and then I stop worrying about things I get a piece of paper or open the notes app and pour random thoughts from my mind on it, this simple process makes me really happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three months ago I publish this blog, quarter of an year! time is actually going so fast, 2021 is almost done (the corona virus is almost two years old now huh!) I never thought I write for more than two weeks or something now this is my &lt;b&gt;12th&lt;/b&gt; post here I just wanted to say thank you (again) to anyone who still read them and care enough to provide me with his opinion and thoughts about them, it means alot to me &amp;lt;3.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">Happiness is for sure one of the hardest topics to talk about, and I know that I said I’ll keep things short and simple, but I actually started this post a few weeks ago.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recipe For A Disaster</title><link href="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/10/15/disaster.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recipe For A Disaster" /><published>2021-10-15T10:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-15T10:45:13+02:00</updated><id>https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/10/15/disaster</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdalraheemmokhtar.github.io/2021/10/15/disaster.html">&lt;p&gt;At your final year in college your graduation project will probably be the most annoying and time consuming task you had to do throughout your entire academic life. And I’m here today to make it even worse, as I hate giving advices to people I’m going to tell you exactly how to make graduation project your way to a mental health facility. So let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choosing-your-group&quot;&gt;Choosing Your Group&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This probably the most important step so please do the minimum amount of thinking before doing it and place your choice solely on one factor and that is how close are you with them. I also recommend not paying any attention to any rational selection criteria like how interested or skilled they are in the topic of your graduation project, or things like their work flow and how much they share your ideas and prioritize the graduation project. I also encourage you to choose someone with contradicted sleep and college schedule so that your chances of meeting with them are way less the less you meet the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choosing-your-topic&quot;&gt;Choosing Your Topic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe this should have been before choosing your group to don’t worry you are in safe hands. Your college will provide you with full support and advices in exchange you’re expected to create a scientific breakthrough in your bachelor degree graduation project so please choose the most advanced and complicated topics that’s currently puzzling the word most elite scientists. My point is: choose a fancy name for your graduation project. Its name has to be prestigious otherwise how would other people know you’re better than them? 
And oh I forgot, please don’t do any initial search about your topic and things like the data you’ll need, limitations, and other boring stuff. These things will magically solve themselves as the semester progress so don’t worry I told you’re in safe hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-supervisor-&quot;&gt;Your supervisor ?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who needs one of these? I’ll tell you: loosers. Wait till the research center of your faculty assign a random supervisor to your project or in case you want to choose from the already available projects you can also choose that randomly, but if you insists you can select a supervisor the same way you choose your group members as mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;workflow&quot;&gt;Workflow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As start working on the project always maintain the least amount of communication between you, your group members, supervisor and the research center. Ensure that problems are discovered as close to the deadlines as possible and then waste that remaining time on blaming each other on who’s fault was that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-the-documentation&quot;&gt;For The Documentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use word or any regular text editor don’t ever waste your time trying to learn latex or anything that’s can make documentation easier. You don’t have to document it step by step, do it all at once and for once no iterative work to gradually enhance your work.
Don’t cite your work I don’t even have to say more about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-the-presentation&quot;&gt;For The Presentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most essential thing in the presentation is to show that you haven’t learned anything useful throughout your work on this project. Pro tip: always agree with the examiners don’t hold your ground and try to defend your work and ideas 
Bounce if you can please show some conflicts or at least ask each other questions about the project during the presentation with your group members this will show the great team spirit that you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations not only you managed to ace your graduation project, you’ve also got the right mindset to start working on your dream career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a short post I know, but I’m kind of busy and not in the mood for writing I’m actully thinking about taking another break until the 17th of November but I’ll probablly publish one or two more before that (as I said before I keep adding to my drafts without being able to finish them) after I finish my degree I’ll try to publish 2-3 post per week unless of course I run out of things to write about but until then I’ll &lt;b&gt;TRY&lt;/b&gt; to keep things shorter and simpler.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdalraheem</name></author><summary type="html">At your final year in college your graduation project will probably be the most annoying and time consuming task you had to do throughout your entire academic life. And I’m here today to make it even worse, as I hate giving advices to people I’m going to tell you exactly how to make graduation project your way to a mental health facility. So let’s get started.</summary></entry></feed>